<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The customers replie. Or Second apologie That is to say, an aunswer to a confused treatise of publicke commerce, printed and dispersed at Midlebourghe and London, in fauour of the priuate Society of Merchants-Aduenturers. By a more serious discourse of exchange in merchandise, and merchandising exchange. Written for vnderstanding readers onely, in fauour of all loyall merchants, and for the aduancing of traffick in England.</title>
            <author>Milles, Tho. (Thomas), 1550?-1627?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 111 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07552</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17932</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114604</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849829</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849829</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15000</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07552)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15000)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 854:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The customers replie. Or Second apologie That is to say, an aunswer to a confused treatise of publicke commerce, printed and dispersed at Midlebourghe and London, in fauour of the priuate Society of Merchants-Aduenturers. By a more serious discourse of exchange in merchandise, and merchandising exchange. Written for vnderstanding readers onely, in fauour of all loyall merchants, and for the aduancing of traffick in England.</title>
                  <author>Milles, Tho. (Thomas), 1550?-1627?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 33, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iames Roberts, dwelling in Barbican,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1604.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Tho: Milles.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Wheeler, John.  A treatise of commerce.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wheeler, John, fl. 1601-1608. --  Treatise of commerce --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Commerce --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15000:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15000:1"/>
            <p>THE CVSTOMERS REPLIE.</p>
            <p>OR SECOND APOLOGIE.</p>
            <p>That is to ſay, An Aunſwer to a confuſed Treatiſe of Publicke Commerce, printed and diſperſed at Midlebourghe and London, in fauour of the priuate Society of MERCHANTS-ADVEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TVRERS.</p>
            <p>By a more ſerious Diſcourſe of EXCHANGE in Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe, and Merchandiſing EXCHANGE.</p>
            <p>Written for vnderſtanding Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders onely, in fauour of all loyall Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, and for the aduancing of TRAFFICK in ENG<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAND.</p>
            <p>AT LONDON, ¶ Printed by <hi>Iames Roberts,</hi> dwelling in Barbican. 1604.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15000:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15000:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RABLE THE LORD <hi>BVCKHVRST,</hi> L. High Treaſurer of England. The Lord <hi>Henrie Howard,</hi> L. Warden of the Cinq-Ports: and the Lord <hi>Cecill</hi> of <hi>Eſenden,</hi> Principall Secretarie of Eſtate to the Kings Maieſtie, and of his Highneſſe moſt honourable Priuie-Counſell.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE NVMBER IS BVT</hi> ſmall, (at leaſt not very great) of men ſo ſenceleſſe or weake of iudgement, but gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall inconveniences they readily ſee, and can eaſily diſcerne. Notwithstanding, to find out the grounds of publique harmes, and the meanes how to cure them, is a ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die ſo intricate, &amp; a practiſe ſo dangerous; that wary men hold it ſafer to prouide for priuate eaſe (in regard of the times) then to buſie theyr wits for anie <hi>common-good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how aduiſed ſoeuer, and reſpectiuely wiſe in this kinde, the most ſort ſeeme to be, as wiſhing onely that all might goe well, though not long of themſelues: fewe or none are found of ſo ſtill a temper, as not to complaine, when publique greefes worke theyr owne ſencible ſmart.</p>
            <p>Such then as by long and extraordinary patience ſupping vp theyr priuate wrongs, haue endeuoured to giue way to the ſtreame of publick contumelies, in hope of better dayes: must needes be excuſed if com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelld at the last by lawleſſe neceſsitie, to referre euents to GODS prouidence, in diſcharge of their Duties to <hi>Him,</hi> their <hi>Prince,</hi> and <hi>Country,</hi> they vndertake the defence of their owne reputations in a Cauſe publicke and generall. The rather, when as without purpoſe of offence towards any, their Intentions appeare, to giue onely a reaſon of ſuch Diſorders in their preſent Functions, as for want of ſerious In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection, or true Information, haue hetherto by Iealouſie and miſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit,
<pb facs="tcp:15000:3"/>yeelded matter and occaſions from time to time of their ſpeciall Diſgraces and obloquie.</p>
            <p>Such and none other, was the drift and ſcope of a late Diſcourſe of the preſent Estate of Customes, not ſo publiquely printed, as pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uately directed <hi>To the Graue and godly vviſe in higheſt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie,</hi> by the Title and Inſcription of <hi>THE CVSTO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MERS APOLOGIE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But. <hi>Pro captu Lectoris habent ſua fata Libelli.</hi> For the booke being written for <hi>vnderſtanding Readers,</hi> and ſo digested, that by reading alone, without paſsion or partialitie, ſuch might be their own and onely Iudges; hath notwithstanding, by the <hi>Ignorant</hi> beene late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cenſured, and ſtrangly mistaken. Vainely ſtriuing to commend &amp; make good that within Booke, which neuer was in question: and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſly vrging ſome things without Booke, that neuer were meant by words nor writing to be defended. But with ſuch ſucceſſe as ſtill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falls <hi>Folly,</hi> who delighting to ſee her owne ſhadow daunce, hath not the grace to conceale her owne ſhame.</p>
            <p>¶ About ſuch time as by the goodnes of GOD, the light of the Goſpell beganne to lay open the Errors of Superstion in theſe parts of the world, and by the hands of our <hi>Soueraignes</hi> to diſperce them in this Kingdome: many Questions were mooued to vphold ſundry poynts of the Popiſh religion; but none ſo hotly diſputed for the time, as that which they terme the <hi>Sacrament of the Alter,</hi> and <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Saints.</hi> Whereof amongst others, a certaine young Scholler more confident then wiſe, hauing vndertaken a ſerious Defence: as one ſicke of loue with the thing he had begotten, and ambiciouſly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting the publiſhing of it; entreated a learned friend of his, &amp; well-minded to the Cauſe, to read it ouer. The request was performed. But looking for Arguments ſitting the Question, When nothing was found but a needleſſe labour, to approoue and maintaine by the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick CREEDE, That IESVS CHRIST, was the true SONNE of GOD, very GOD, and very MAN that redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the Worlde:</hi> And that there was alſo a <hi>COMMVNION OF SAINTS.</hi> The Booke was returned without applaude, or ſhew of ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>RIGHT HONORABLE.</hi> Such hath beene of late yeeres, the ſucceſſe of a like learned Writer, who printing, <hi>A Treatiſe of publique Commerce,</hi> in fauour of the priuate Societie of the <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants-Aduenturers,</hi> hath with much a-doe, and a heape of ſillie words, (farre vnfitting the grauitie of his Theame) endeuoured to
<pb facs="tcp:15000:3"/>perſwade his Readers, <hi>That Trafficke rightly ordered, is the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of Kings, and proſperitie of Kingdoms:</hi> And that <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants</hi> in that reſpect, <hi>were to be cheriſhed, fauoured, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged in all Common-wealths.</hi> Quia <hi>VITA CIVILIS IN SOCIETATE POSITA EST, SOCIETAS AV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TEM IN IMPERIO ET COMMERCIO.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is ſtrange to obſerue, what ſtrong apprehentions are able to worke in weake mens braines. For as a plaine ſimple man was ſometimes perſwaded, that if <hi>Pontius Pilate</hi> had not beene a Saint, the Apoſtles would neuer haue ſuffered his Name to ſtand in the <hi>Creede:</hi> ſo this <hi>Treatiſe-Writer,</hi> by a ſtrong imagination of the <hi>Merchant-Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturers</hi> extraordinary deſerts: ſeeing the admirable effects of the golden bleſsings of England, by turning <hi>Creekes</hi> into <hi>Ports,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Read the Treatiſe printed at Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleburgh, anno. 1601.</note> ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Ports</hi> vnto <hi>Townes,</hi> rayſing <hi>Townes</hi> into <hi>Citties,</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riching whole Countries with <hi>Artificers</hi> and <hi>Trades, Marriners</hi> &amp; <hi>Shipping.</hi> Applauding withall, theyr ſinguler happines, and great good fortunes, to haue the managing thereof within themſelues. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending their<note n="*" place="margin">The Merchants Aduenturers, boaſt themſelues to bee able to make and diuert a Trade, at their pleaſures. Page, 23.</note> dexterities, in <hi>diſpoſing, diuerting, deuiding, mincing, abridging, reſtrayning,</hi> and lastly <hi>confining</hi> the <hi>Store</hi> and <hi>Staple</hi> thereof within the Walles of ſome one two Townes for beſt aduantage in<note n="*" place="margin">Marke this well by the way, for heerein lyes hid, The Pot of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</note> 
               <hi>Forraine Countries,</hi> culloured with the Title of their ſpeciall <hi>Mart-Townes.</hi> And aboue all things extolling their excellent wits, and abſolute cunnings, in moulding Lawes by meere Diſcretion, to hold all men vnder, and themſelues aboue. Onely for ſending or ſayling croſſe the Seas from Coast to Coast, without ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of their Perſons, or loſſe of their Goods more then vſuall &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary. And for wearing<note n="*" place="margin">Page, 154. 155. 156.</note> 
               <hi>Chaines of gold about their Necks, Caps and greene Feathers, Hats and white Feathers, Buskins of purple Veluet, guilt Rapiers, Daggers, Bridles, Stirrops, Spurres,</hi> and ſuch like, at <hi>Tryumphs,</hi> and <hi>publique meetings.</hi> But ſpecially for <hi>feeding, maintayning,</hi> and <hi>ſetting</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">At Antwerpe. 20000. About Antwerpe, 30000. In Flaunders, 60000. Page, 24.</note> 
               <hi>thouſands</hi> on worke <hi>beyond-Seas,</hi> when God knowes the wants, &amp; heares the cryes <hi>at home:</hi> would faine perſwade others, (beeing bound to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire them himſelfe,) That their <hi>Gouernour</hi> is for Skill the<note n="*" place="margin">Pontius.</note> 
               <hi>PI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LOT,</hi> for Grauitie the <hi>Iudge,</hi> and for Wiſedome the <hi>Oracle</hi> of all orderly <hi>Commerce.</hi> Their priuate<note n="*" place="margin">Talmud.</note> 
               <hi>DECREES,</hi> aboue <hi>COMMON LAVVES,</hi> and <hi>FORRAINE-TREATISE.</hi> Theyr particuler<note n="*" place="margin">Synhedry.</note> 
               <hi>SYNODES,</hi> aboue <hi>GENERALL COVNSAILES,</hi> and their<note n="*" place="margin">Synagogue.</note> 
               <hi>SOCIETY</hi> a <hi>COMMV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NION OF SAINTS.</hi> Pronouncing all that diſlike, distaste, or distrust their <hi>Doctrine,</hi> for <hi>EN TER-LO PERS.</hi> That is to
<pb facs="tcp:15000:4"/>ſay,<note n="*" place="margin">All Engliſh, Chriſtian, &amp; loyall Merchants, Crucifige.</note> 
               <hi>Sciſmaticks, Hereticks,</hi> and <hi>Infidels,</hi> vnwoorthy to breath Common-ayre, or liue in any Common-Wealth. Concluding ſtrongly withall, That theſe <hi>Men</hi> thus put in trust with the credite and Creame of the Kingdome, <hi>(our Cloth,)</hi> must needes bee hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den more loyall to their <hi>Prince,</hi> more ſeruiceable to the <hi>State,</hi> more welcome to their <hi>Neighbours,</hi> and therefore more to be honoured, then any other <hi>Men,</hi> with a Name aboue all Names, of <hi>MER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHANTS-ADVENTVRERS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With this and ſuch like ſtuffe the Booke beeing confuſedly fraught, <hi>(cuius contrarium veriſsimum eſt,)</hi> might well haue beene ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to haue dyed in the birth, if withall it had not beene mingled with aſpertions of obloquy &amp; vntruthes againſt <hi>CVSTOMERS of the Out-Ports of the Realme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>CVSTOMERS.</hi> A kinde of Creatures capable of Religion aſwell as Reaſon: free Men by birth, and of best education. Men euery way happy, ſaue in their Names and Callings: and in nothing more wretched then in the Places of their Functions. <hi>The Out-Ports of the Realme.</hi>
               <note place="margin">London the onely Port of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. all other Ports are counted but Out-Ports, to London.</note> O holy <hi>LONDON!</hi> Men I ſay, that being by the curious eye of the Law, <hi>Choſen of the beſt,</hi> and placed in the ranke <hi>of the moſt ſufficient</hi> that Wiſedome can finde, or choiſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford; would faine retaine the reputations,<note place="margin">The Law is as carefull in the choiſe of a Cuſtomer, as of a Shriefe of the Shiere.</note> if not of <hi>Saints,</hi> yet at the least of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and plaine <hi>honeſt Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To let it therefore in ſome ſort appeare, that it is not enough for Men affecting their owne good &amp; credits by <hi>Traffick,</hi> to value theyr worths by diſgracing of others; and that by ſuch kind of Imputations &amp; Shifts,<note place="margin">Cuſtomers are no Prophets; to geſſe by the Goods, of what Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the Owner is, it beeing a myſterie among Merchants, to lend hands, and culloure one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others dealing.</note> as none but Merchants (perhaps themſelues that thus byte and whine,) onely or most vſually commit, and is not in the <hi>Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers</hi> power to preuent or amend: that which enſueth, hath beene wrung from them by way of further Defence. For though it might be ſaid, That to aunſwere all priuate oppoſitions were fruitleſſe, and to no end: yet least he that runnes alone, ſhould ſtill thinke himſelfe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most: to ſatisfie <hi>Wiſedome</hi> and <hi>Authoritie</hi> it ſelfe,<note place="margin">The Treatiſe hath beene twice printed at Midleburge and Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and dedicated to the Lord Cecill.</note> I haue beene prouoked (by words &amp; writings) out of other Mens labours and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer experience, (as by way of witnes) to make good that for <hi>Traffick,</hi> which the <hi>Apologie</hi> before did but tenderly touch, and briefelie ſet downe.</p>
            <p>Beſides. Not to ſhew the decay of thoſe Effects which both main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> Credits, and giue Eſſence to their Functions, by the occaſions of the Ecclyps in their <hi>Cauſe Efficient:</hi> were wittingly to betray the generall <hi>good</hi> of all Men, &amp; worthily to ſet down in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall obloquy. And publique ſlaunders are not waſht off but by
<pb facs="tcp:15000:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>publicke Defence.</p>
            <p>For <hi>TRAFFICK</hi> therefore: <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> beeing bound, and bold to contend, the aduancement whereof, like Hony in Hiues, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth Customes.<note n="*" place="margin">The childiſh commendation of <hi>Trafficke,</hi> by the <hi>Treatiſe-writer.</hi> Page. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Not that Commerce, which children aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoone as theyr tongues are at liberty doe ſeaſon their ſports by: Nor that which Weomen among themſelues doe chop and change by:</hi> But that <hi>TRAFFICK</hi> whoſe Lawes at the Standart of Equitie, wey out Order, (not by priuate Diſcretion, nor partiall Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection) but by the weight of generall Iustice. Whoſe <hi>Merchants</hi> are Perſons all euery where Loyall and friendly. Whoſe <hi>Ports</hi> &amp; <hi>Staples</hi> at home, <hi>Markets</hi> &amp; <hi>Marts</hi> at home &amp; abroade, are places for acceſſe conueniently <hi>eaſie,</hi> and for ſafety generally <hi>free.</hi> And whoſe <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe,</hi> for <hi>Matter</hi> honest, for <hi>Vſe</hi> profitable, by <hi>Nature</hi> admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and by <hi>Art</hi> made amiable, is at all handes vendible onely for the <hi>Goodnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>TRAFFICK,</hi> I ſay, whoſe diuine Elixar <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> the quinteſſence of <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Art</hi> applied to Materialls, breedes Misteries in <hi>Trades,</hi> turnes <hi>Trades</hi> into Mettals, and all Mettals into pure Siluer, and fine Golde. The restauring power whereof, eaſing all griefes in Sores, ſuppling all Sores in diſeaſes, and curing all Diſeaſes in particular Members, holdes the whole Bodies of <hi>Kingdomes</hi> in health. Lastlie: That <hi>TRAFFICK</hi> which concernes <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> whoſe ſeate is euery where the <hi>Soueraignes</hi> boſome. Whoſe voyce well tuned, is the harmonie of the World, To whom <hi>Courts</hi> and <hi>Countries</hi> owe fealtie and homage, the meanest <hi>Subiects</hi> feeling her care, &amp; the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test <hi>Princes</hi> ſubiect to her prouidence. Whom both <hi>Noble</hi> and <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble</hi> admire, as the <hi>Nurſſe</hi> of all their earthly honors, proſperities, peace and ioy. To the end, I ſay, that by other mens complaints, as well as <hi>Cuſtomers,</hi> the world may ſee how hunted, restrained, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopoliſed, and ill beholden, that <hi>TRAFFICK</hi> is &amp; hath been to all <hi>priuate Societies.</hi> In the Fore-Ranck whereof I ſet the<note n="*" place="margin">This is heere added, onely that the <hi>Treatiſe-writer</hi> might exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the grounds of his ovvne folly or frenzie in taxing Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers as friends to the <hi>Haunces,</hi> by ſpeaking againſt his <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants-Aduenturers.</hi> To whom, as to <hi>Subiects,</hi> onely for their <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraignes</hi> ſake, they wiſh all kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and loue, but reuerence ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as <hi>abſolute Princes.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>HAVN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CES,</hi> (that beeing but <hi>Subiects</hi> a part and a ſunder vnder ſeuerall <hi>Soueraignes;</hi> yet combined together, dare contest with <hi>Princes:</hi>) and theſe our <hi>MERCHANTS-ADVENTVRERS,</hi> as her two most wayward and wrangling children. Who preferring particuler <hi>Decrees</hi> before generall <hi>Treatiſe</hi> and <hi>Lawes,</hi> &amp; with publick wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons maintayning contentions for priuate wrongs; in ſteed of <hi>Order</hi> pretended, breede nothing but complaints at home, confuſions within themſelues, endleſſe troubles to graue <hi>Counſailes</hi> at <hi>Counſaile-Tables,</hi> and vnkind Iarres betweene <hi>Kingdomes, States, Allies,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:15000:5"/>and forraine <hi>Neighbour-friendes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Leauing therefore the <hi>TREATISE-WRITER</hi> to beleeue ſtill in the <hi>CREEDE,</hi> whoſe Articles are certainely moſt holy and true, though <hi>Pontius Pilates</hi> Name ſtand for no Saint: And the <hi>MERCHANTS-ADVENTVRERS</hi> to the Story of <hi>ISIS.</hi> Whoſe Image of gold it was that men ſo admired, in all places where it came, and not the beautie of the Beast that bare it. I referre your Wiſedomes and Honourable patience, to the <hi>Counter-Treatiſe</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing: beeing a plaine Demonstration of that Canker of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, MERCHANDISING-EXCHANGE.</hi> I ſay a cleere de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of that Contempt of <hi>Lawes,</hi> Diſdaine of <hi>Equity,</hi> Scorne of publique <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> Diſhonour of <hi>Princes,</hi> and Mysterie of <hi>Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie.</hi> And a liuely Deſcription of that<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SVRIE.</note> 
               <hi>Monſter</hi> of <hi>CREETE,</hi> deuouring as it were by yeerely tribute, the bodies of <hi>Men,</hi> &amp; ſoules of <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> His <hi>hatching</hi> and <hi>broode,</hi> his <hi>Muces</hi> &amp; <hi>haunts,</hi> his <hi>Practiſe</hi> and <hi>Shifts,</hi> his <hi>Shape</hi> and <hi>Name,</hi> vnder the Title of <hi>MERCHANDIZING-EXCHANGE.</hi> The <hi>Laborinth</hi> of whoſe inextricable Errors, none may ſafelie enter, &amp; whoſe <hi>Perſon</hi> none can encounter and quell, but <hi>fatall THESEVS,</hi> aſsisted by the thred of addreſſe and Counſaile of <hi>ARIADNE.</hi> A worke ſometimes proiected to giue light vnto others,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1565"/> but happily reſerued to honour your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> and theſe our dayes withall.</p>
            <p>And ſince the caſe of <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> ſtands ſo farre preiudged, that euen theyr Cryes ſeeme but Ecchoes in the<note n="*" place="margin">Out-Torts.</note> 
               <hi>Deſerts,</hi> round about the <hi>Plaines,</hi> neere the <hi>FORREST OF SHIFTS,</hi> the ſound whereof most men paſſe by but heare not, many heare but vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not, ſome few vnderſtand but regard not, and no man pitties. And that their painful <hi>Apologies</hi> are left to the <hi>Ignorant,</hi> to proſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute publiquely, and turne into Sinne: whilst they ſit ſtill in ſilence, like <hi>Barnes ſo ding'd that they dare not greit:</hi> Let <hi>Experience</hi> tell <hi>IELOVSIE,</hi> how ſhe torments <hi>TRAFFICK,</hi> by clogging her<note n="*" place="margin">Custome ſeruice.</note> 
               <hi>Seruice</hi> with ſwarms of ſuch <hi>Inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts</hi> as loue her Cuſtoms, but as Rats do loue Cheeſe. And let <hi>Nature</hi> tell <hi>SVSPITION</hi> howe <hi>TRAFFICK</hi> appeales. That whilst her<note n="*" place="margin">Custome houſes.</note> 
               <hi>HOVSES</hi> as Places infected, or haunted with Sprites, are either abandond, or by Extremities made ſubiect to Shifts: The <hi>Free-will Offerings.</hi> The Effects of <hi>Loyaltie.</hi> The <hi>True-loue-knots,</hi> knit betweene <hi>Subiects</hi> &amp; <hi>Prince.</hi> And Tokens of<note n="*" place="margin">Customes.</note> 
               <hi>Affection</hi> (religiouſly moued in <hi>Minds,</hi> admiring the glorious <hi>OBIECT</hi> of their owne welfare &amp; <hi>Good</hi>) from the harts of her <hi>Merchants,</hi> humbly preſented to <hi>Soueraigne Dignitie,</hi> and to None other due. Become now ſet to ſale. As if
<pb facs="tcp:15000:5"/>franck-harted <hi>Loue,</hi> &amp; true-louing <hi>Loyalty</hi> (the <hi>Homage</hi> of <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects,</hi> and <hi>Honor</hi> of <hi>KINGS.</hi>) Were <hi>Thinges</hi> transferrent from that <hi>Prerogatiue</hi> which giues them life and <hi>Beeing.</hi> Or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to <hi>Exchange.</hi> Or vendible for <hi>Money.</hi> Or fit for<note n="*" place="margin">The Farming out of Cuſtomes, offenſiue to Nature: and vnto Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick meerely <hi>Heterocli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>FAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MORS.</hi> Dryuing <hi>TRAFFICK</hi> thus from the Lyme-kill to the Cole-pit: euery way decaying her <hi>PORTS,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Et <hi>Licentijs</hi> ſumus omnes deteriores.</note> &amp; diſgracing her <hi>Seruaunts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as inveterate Errors, hold still their aduantage, and are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ouerthrowne, till from <hi>Signes</hi> vnto <hi>Cauſes,</hi> by Effects it appeare how the Worlde in Matter of <hi>TRAFFICK</hi> hath beene abuſed, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-ruled, and ouer-ſeene: So when <hi>TRVTH,</hi> the Daughter of <hi>TIME,</hi> by practiſe and proofe ſhall be brought to light, then ſhall <hi>Ignorance</hi> and <hi>Impudencie</hi> ſtand both confounded, &amp; <hi>IELO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIE</hi> herſelfe ſee that in <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> vertue is not vice.</p>
            <p>For if it be true that <hi>Truth</hi> hath ſworne, <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, &amp; <hi>Experience</hi> confirmes. To wit: That looke what the <hi>Soule</hi> is to the outward actions of the <hi>Body,</hi> in ordering each Member, ſo as to <hi>Nature</hi> ſeemes fittest for the good of the <hi>whole Man:</hi> the ſame is <hi>TRAFFICK</hi> in diſpoſing <hi>Myſteries</hi> and <hi>Trades</hi> to the behoofe of the <hi>Common-Wealth.</hi> The<note n="*" place="margin">The King.</note> 
               <hi>DAY-STARRE</hi> is riſen, and the<note n="*" place="margin">The Prince.</note> 
               <hi>DAVVNING</hi> appeares, which giuing life to our Hopes, makes vs breath out thus much, and ſay: The time may come, when this hartie zeale of ours to our <hi>SOVERAIGNES</hi> honour, and his <hi>Peoples</hi> happines, may be better regarded, and deſerue not onely thanks and good words, but make all men confeſſe themſelues (<hi>Merchants</hi> at least) to owe as much to theſe weake endeuours of <hi>CVSTOMERS,</hi> euen thoſe of the deſpiſed <hi>Out-Ports of this Realme,</hi> I ſay not as one <hi>Port,</hi> one <hi>Towne,</hi> or one Citty of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> but many <hi>Ports,</hi> many <hi>Townes,</hi> and many Citties like <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and all their wealth beſides are worth, ſome few <hi>priuate, parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer,</hi> and <hi>preuenting</hi> Perſons excepted. The Cenſure whereof I most humbly ſubmit to <hi>Iudgement</hi> and <hi>Wiſedome,</hi> with this <hi>Caution</hi> &amp; finall <hi>Concluſion.</hi> That <hi>TRVTH</hi> lyes deepe, and few there are that vndertake the toyle to delue till they finde her. And though <hi>Publique harmes</hi> &amp; <hi>priuate Diſgaces</hi> to <hi>men</hi> of my Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, haue ſingled me foorth, and preſſed mee forward to worke thus alone, for the <hi>Common-good;</hi> the burden whereof makes mee cry aloude: I must confeſſe, that in theſe <hi>Apologies,</hi> and forced <hi>Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> (accuſing no man, for that was the Deuils part from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, nor at warre with any but Sinne and Diſhonestie) <hi>Nil magis in Votis nec habui, nec habeo, quam vt inter plures, aliquos
<pb facs="tcp:15000:6"/>inveniam, qui de iſtis judicare queant. Iudicare autem non poſſunt niſi vtcunque Literati, aut Rerum vſu periti. Ex hijs ſatis mihj pauci Lectores, ſat erit ſi vel vnus:</hi> In Appealing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to the <hi>GRAVEST</hi> and <hi>WISEST</hi> in <hi>HIGHEST AV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THORITY.</hi> I haue thought it meetest &amp; ſafest for triple reſpects, to preſent <hi>my ſelfe,</hi> and my poore <hi>ſeruice,</hi> to your <hi>honorable Lordſhips,</hi> by whoſe ſpeciall fauours next <hi>GOD</hi> and my <hi>SOVERAIGNE,</hi> I am that I am, and ſo deſire to be knowne.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your LL: by ſeuerall Duties. deuotedly bound.</hi> Tho: Milles.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:15000:6"/>
            <head>THE CHAPTERS CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TAYNING the matter handled in this TREATISE.</head>
            <list>
               <item>¶ A Preface or Introduction to the Matter handled in the Treatiſe of <hi>Exchange.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>¶ 1 The Antiquity, neceſsity, &amp; vſe of Lawfull <hi>Exchange,</hi> and a Deſcription thereof.</item>
               <item>¶ 2 How Merchants haue deuiſed and introduced another kind of <hi>Exchange,</hi> called <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>¶ 3 The Compacts and Conditions commonly agreed vpon in <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>¶ 4 The termes of Arte proper to <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange,</hi> by diuerſities of <hi>Times,</hi> and Diſtances of <hi>Place.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>¶ 5 The Diuerſitie of prices of Money currant in <hi>Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſing Exchange,</hi> according to the Diſtances of <hi>Place,</hi> &amp; difference of <hi>Tymes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>¶ 6 The manner of rayſing the valuation of Money in <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>¶ 7 The Difference betweene the Lawfull <hi>Exchange,</hi> and <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>¶ 8 The firſt ſtanding <hi>Bankes</hi> and <hi>Pillers</hi> of <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange.</hi> And a Deſcription thereof.</item>
               <item>¶ 9 Three Practiſes, and fiue Abuſes hurtfull and pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to all Common-wealths by <hi>Merchandiſing Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>¶ 10 How and by whom the practiſing of <hi>Merchandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Exchange,</hi> is the Cauſe of all exceſsiue prices in Commodities &amp; things vendible: to the preventing &amp; perverting of all lawfull <hi>Traffick</hi> &amp; orderly <hi>Dealing</hi> within the Realme &amp; Common-wealth of England.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:15000:7"/>
               <item>¶ An <hi>Abridgement</hi> of the ſpeciall Inconueniences to this Realme of England, handled in the foreſayd tenth Chapter.</item>
               <item>¶ A generall Concluſion.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15000:7"/>
            <head>A TREATISE Of EXCHANGE in <hi>Merchandiſe, and Merchandiſing</hi> EXCHANGE.</head>
            <head type="sub">¶ A Preface or Introduction to the Matter handled in the Treatiſe of EXCHANGE.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ll things whatſoeuer tend naturally to ſome</hi> End. Which <hi>End</hi> beeing the <hi>Perfection</hi> of that for which it worketh, is onely attaind vnto by apt &amp; fit <hi>Meanes.</hi> That which appoynts &amp; moderates <hi>fitnes</hi> &amp; <hi>Forme</hi> in working, is termed a <hi>Law:</hi> by which, as by <hi>Rules,</hi> the World and all things therein are diſtinguiſht and ſtinted. Which Limitation is both the <hi>Perfection</hi> and <hi>Preſeruation</hi> of the Things themſelues. <hi>Meaſure</hi> therefore working by <hi>Proportions,</hi> is the way, to <hi>Perfection.</hi> And ſince nothing doth perriſh, but through the <hi>too much</hi> or <hi>too little</hi> of that, the due proportioned <hi>Meaſure</hi> whereof dooth giue <hi>Perfection; Meaſure</hi> is alſo the <hi>Preſeruation</hi> of all Things. For to <hi>Proportion, Exceſſe</hi> and <hi>Defects</hi> are oppoſites. <hi>Iuſtice</hi> then beeing the foreconceiued <hi>End</hi> of all Actions, is preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed and perfitted by <hi>Lawes,</hi> and preſerued by <hi>Meaſures.</hi> Which beeing the Heauenly charge of Earthly Princes; ſets foorth &amp; lymits their <hi>Soueraignties</hi> &amp; <hi>Prerogatiues</hi> ſacred &amp; royall, otherwiſe (in regard of their humane Subſtances and qualities) tranſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dent. For it is ſaid, <hi>They are Gods</hi> in regard of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> but theyr <hi>Perſons</hi> ſhall die like Men. <hi>Iuſtice</hi> is <hi>Diſtributiue</hi> or <hi>Commutatiue. Commutatiue Iuſtice</hi> encludeth <hi>Traffick.</hi> The end of <hi>Traffick</hi> is <hi>Equalitie</hi> in ſupplying Neceſsities, <hi>vt quod vſpiam naſcitur Boni id apud omnes affluat:</hi> eyther by bartring wares for wares, or by ſome Midds or <hi>Meanes</hi> certaine and indifferent to preuent <hi>Aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>End</hi> therefore in <hi>Traffick</hi> beeing <hi>Equitie,</hi> and the vſe <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change;</hi> the <hi>Meaſure</hi> is by publicke Conſent of all Nations called <hi>Money.</hi> And as the <hi>Standart</hi> of all kind of <hi>Meaſures</hi> for generall <hi>Iuſtice</hi> like <hi>Vrim</hi> and <hi>Thummim</hi> is the Princes charge onely: gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15000:8"/>thereby <hi>Weight</hi> and <hi>Content, Length</hi> and <hi>Breadth</hi> to all <hi>Proportions:</hi> So the coyning of <hi>Money</hi> and the valuation thereof, being a <hi>Meaſure</hi> of principall Excellency and peculiar to <hi>Trafficke,</hi> is immediatly, <hi>Vni ſoli et ſemper,</hi> an eſſentiall part of <hi>Soueraigne Authority.</hi> Out of which Premiſſes, this muſt be concluded. That either to coyne <hi>Money,</hi> or being coyned to alter the true <hi>Valuation</hi> thereof, in what kind ſoeuer; is in Subiectes whoſoeuer, when and whereſoeuer, to preſume vpon the Maieſtie of <hi>Soueraigne Princes,</hi> to prophane the Sacred Seate of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> to contemne publicke <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> and in <hi>Trafficke</hi> to preuent and peruert all <hi>order</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</hi> A Capitall ſinne againſt God and Nature.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>Thus much only being added by way of</hi> Preface, <hi>by the Cuſtomers of the Out-Ports, who for the</hi> Effectes <hi>ſake are euery way bound to aduance the</hi> Cauſe: <hi>That which followes of the</hi> Matter <hi>and vſe of</hi> Trafficke, <hi>is proper to Merchants. Heare therfore a loyall Marchants experience, writing in his owne Stile and Phraſe of</hi> Exchange <hi>in</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe, <hi>and</hi> Marchandiſing <hi>Exchange, in Order as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tractent Fabrilia Fabri.</p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> ¶ The Antiquitie, neceſsity, and vſe of Lawfull <hi>Exchange,</hi> and a Deſcription thereof.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T IS APPARANT TO SVCH AS are converſant in Records of tyme and olde Wryters, that the exerciſe of <hi>Exchange</hi> is a thing of greateſt antiquitie: borne with <hi>Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick</hi> it ſelfe, and as it ſeemeth, begate the firſt Names and Titles of thoſe which are called in Latine, <hi>Numularii, Argentarii,</hi> and <hi>Coly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bistae,</hi> that is to ſay, publique and common Exchangers, and Commutors of Bullyon, ſtrange and forraine coynes to all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Strangers, for the lawfull and currant money of thoſe Countryes and Common-wealths, where the ſaid <hi>Exchange</hi> was <hi>proportioned</hi> and <hi>authoriſed</hi> by the Princes &amp; Gouernors of the ſame.</p>
               <p>And becauſe the Office of <hi>Exchanging,</hi> and curteſie of len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding money in a Common-wealth, after an eaſie &amp; tollerable
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15000:8"/>reckoning, is very neceſſary and expedient. The olde Ciuill Lawes did graunt and permit to this honeſt kind of <hi>Exchange,</hi> a certaine rate in the hundred by the yeere, for th'intereſt of ſuch money as was lent to ſuch as had neede.</p>
               <p>And a certaine exerciſe and vſe of the ſame was ſometime allowed and admitted in England, as when the Tables of <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change</hi> were ſet vp, &amp; erected in diuers Townes thereof, in the time of King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, and other Kings raignes ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding him.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Exchangers</hi> &amp; Keepers of which Tables, did change to all manner of Forraine Marchants and Strangers, which reſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thether: aſwell Bullion, as all forraine coynes and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neies which they brought thether for the currant Money of the Realme, according to the Princes iuſt valuation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
               <p>And this manner of <hi>Exchange,</hi> ſeemeth alſo to be the firſt occaſion of the erecting of thoſe ſhops of <hi>Exchange,</hi> which at this day bee called in Spaine and Italy <hi>Cambios</hi> and <hi>Bancos,</hi> which at the firſt inſtitution of them were appointed for great ſafegarde, and commoditie of ſuch as had Money, for that they might without danger lay into the ſayd <hi>Cambios</hi> and <hi>Banckes</hi> (as it were <hi>in Depoſito</hi>) what ſums of Money they would, for the which the Cambiadors and Bankars would be anſwerable, as for a thing depoſited, and committed to their cuſtody, and would alſo make payments thereof, according to the order of the ſayd Depoſitor. Which farther did vſe to <hi>change</hi> Siluer for Gold, and all manner of forraine coyne and Money, for the lawfull and currant Money of thoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryes, and that according to the lawfull valuation of the ſame. And moreouer, by theſe Cambiadors or Bankars, ſometime there was wayes and meanes taken, to make <hi>Exchange</hi> of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, from one Country to another: for ſuch as had occaſion for to trauell and paſſe Countryes. Likewiſe according to the iuſt and publique valuation of ſuch coyne and Monies, the reward and ſalary of Cambiadors for their labors and paines in keeping Money, <hi>Exchanging</hi> white Money for Gold, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine coynes for the lawfull and currant Money of Spaine, within this thirty yeeres, was not aboue two and a halfe in the thouſand, for the ſpace of on Faire, which commonly endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth there ſix weekes, and this intereſt and gaines amounteth not aboue three in the hundred for the whole yeere.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:15000:9"/>
               <p>This manner of <hi>Exchange</hi> is not onely to be ſuffered &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in a Common-wealth: but as it appeareth, very neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, expedient, and commodious to the ſame: not onely for the exchanging of Bullyon and coynes within the ſelfe ſame Realme and Common-wealth: but alſo for the paſſing of Money from one Country to another, for ſuch as haue affaires to trauell Countries as the Embaſſadors of Princes do: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by be diuers perrils auoyded that they ſhould runne in, carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ready Money about them. So that the ſayd <hi>Exchange</hi> be not practiſed of ſuch as traffick Merchandiſe, and will imploy theyr money ſo exchanged againe in wares and commodities to be returned into theyr owne Countrey. For to all ſuch the ſayd <hi>Exchange</hi> was alwayes prohibited in England, as a thing diſcommodious and pernicious, both to the Prince and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, as may appeare by diuers Acts of Parliament, prouided to that end.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">EXCHANGE deſcribed.</note>¶ <hi>Exchange</hi> therfore is a certaine lawfull kind of commutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and changing of Money, appointed by the publick autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of a Common-wealth, eyther for the changing of Bullyon ſtrange and forraine coynes brought thither, according to ſuch valuation as the ſayd Bullyon and coynes haue, or be eſteemed at, by the common authority of the ſame Common-wealth and Country.</p>
               <p>Or elſe it is a certaine meanes, for the commutation and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changing of Money from one Realme or Country to another, according to the iuſt and lawfull valuation of Money priced &amp; ſet foorth by the publicke authority of ſuch Countries and Realmes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> How Merchants haue deuiſed and introduced another kind of <hi>Exchange.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BVT vnder the coullor and pretence of this lawfull <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change</hi> and commutation of Money, Merchants of late yeeres haue deuiſed and brought vp another manner of <hi>Exchange</hi> of coyne: to the which they doe alſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly giue this plaine and ſimple name, <hi>Exchanging:</hi> vvhen indeed it is not ſo, but a meere faeneration, and a making a ware and merchandize of Money: for that in the ſame, and by the ſame they buy and ſell, rayſe and abate the price of Money, as
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15000:9"/>well as they doe rayſe and abate the price of any other vvare &amp; Merchandizes they traffick in. Wherefore it is not to be called ſimply <hi>Exchange,</hi> but properly and aptly to be called the <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandizing of Money.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet becauſe that through the practiſe and pollicy of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, ſpecially trading &amp; frequenting the Marts of <hi>Antwerpe,</hi> and the Fayres of <hi>Lions,</hi> for the paſſing of Money from place to place by the ſame, which alſo is done after a certaine ſort and kind of exchanging and commuting of Money, it may conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently be called &amp; haue the name of <hi>Merchandizing Exchange.</hi> Foraſmuch as Money paſſed and exchanged after this way and manner, muſt be payd againe according to the conditions and compacts taken and agreed vpon with the Merchants, for the price &amp; valuation therof: and not according to the iuſt &amp; law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full valuation it hath by any publicke Authority of that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, which is author of the ſayd Money: the vvhich temerarius alteration of publick coynes &amp; monyes, is the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall foundation of the ſayd <hi>Exchange;</hi> and of the gaines and lucar proceeding of the ſame: for the loue &amp; greedines wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the other lawfull <hi>Exchange</hi> is exiled and expelled both out of Spaine and Italie; and through the frequenting thereof, the trade of Merchandiſe is corrupted in all Countries, and ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in England, by the buſie practiſing thereof of Merchants betweene Antwerpe and England, which haue brought many inconveniences vnto this Common-wealth, &amp; be thereby the onely Authors, why all manner of wares and Merchandizes beare ſuch exceſsiue prices as they doe at this day within the Realme, as heereafter ſhall be declared, by the opening of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine circumſtances eſſentially appertayning to the ſame <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change,</hi> without the which it can neither be vnderſtood nor practiſed; and ſo ſhall it euidently appeare, that all th'inormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties diſordering the prices of all manner of things vendible in the Common-wealth, haue theyr originall from thence.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> The Compacts and Conditions commonly agreed vpon in <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FIrſt, the taker and Receiuer of Money by this <hi>Exchange,</hi> muſt compound &amp; agree with the Deliuerer of the ſame, at what <hi>diſtance</hi> of <hi>time</hi> the ſayde Money ſhall be payde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15000:10"/>in a forraine Country or Citty appointed for the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof, for there bee three kindes of diuerſities, and Diſtances of time moſt commonly in vſe at this day amongſt <hi>Merchants,</hi> for the repayment of ſuch Money as is taken and deliuered by this <hi>Exchange.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, the taker and Receiuor of Money by this <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change,</hi> muſt compound and agree with the Deliuerer thereof, to make payment againe in the forraine Country, according as the ſame Money receiued is valued by the <hi>Merchants,</hi> to bee worth in the currant Money of the ſame forraine Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and according to the price and valuation the ſayd currant Mony hath in this their <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange,</hi> and not after the Princes iuſt valuation of the ſame Money.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> The Termes of Art proper to <hi>Marchandiſing Exchange,</hi> by diuerſities of <hi>Times,</hi> and Diſtances of <hi>Place.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe firſt kind of diuerſity, <hi>Merchants</hi> call the taking and deliuering of Money <hi>at ſight,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">At ſigh.</note> the cuſtome wherof in this <hi>Exchange</hi> &amp; commutation, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelleth the Receiuor of the Money vpon a litle Scedule or Bill, containing the ſumme &amp; value of the forraine coyne and Money, which muſt be payd againe to the vſe of the Deliuerer, immediatly as the ſaid Sce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dule &amp; Bill ſhall be ſhewed and preſented by the Deliuerer or his Factor, to the Factor or Seruant of the ſaid taker and Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor of Money, or els to his owne ſelfe.</p>
               <p>The ſecond, is to take and deliuer Money by or at <hi>Vſance,</hi> and the cuſtome of this diuerſity compelleth the taker of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney by this <hi>Exchange,</hi> vppon his Bill or Scedule to pay the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue thereof againe in forraine coyne or Money, at the end of one month next immediatly ended, after the firſt daie of the making of the <hi>Exchange,</hi> in the Towne or Citty appointed thereunto in the ſay Scedule: either by himſelfe, his Factor or Seruant.</p>
               <p>This ſpace of time of one month, is limited for this ſecond Diſtance of time in this <hi>Marchandiſing Exchange,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vſance.</note> called <hi>Vſance,</hi> betweene <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Antwerp,</hi> and other Marting Townes there-abouts, by the Bankers and <hi>Exchangers</hi> of the ſame <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:15000:10"/>
               <p>The third is called <hi>Double Vſance,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Double Vſance.</note> by the vſe and cuſtome whereof, the Taker and Receiuer of Money by the ſame <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change,</hi> is compelled by his Bill or Scedule, to pay the value thereof againe in forraine Money at the end of two months next, immediatly ending after the day that the Money was firſt taken vp by <hi>Exchange,</hi> either by himſelfe, Factor, or Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, in the place appointed and aſſigned thereunto by the ſayd Scedule.</p>
               <p>And heere is to be noted, that theſe two latter Diſtances of time, be made longer and ſhorter for the payment of Money taken vp by the ſame, after the diuerſitie of any of the ſayd two kindes, according to the Diſtance of the Places, for the which the ſay <hi>Exchange</hi> is or ſhall be made at any time.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> The Diuerſitie of Prices of Money currant in <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange,</hi> according to the Diſtances of <hi>Place,</hi> and difference of <hi>Times.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>LIke as the time and ſpaces limited to euery diuerſity and Diſtance of time &amp; place, of this <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange,</hi> differ and vary one from another, betweene <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Antwerp,</hi> and other Marting Townes thereabouts: ſo hath th'engliſh pound paſſed by this <hi>Exchange,</hi> betweene the one Country and the other, at diuers and ſundry prices, differing one from another, according to the time it is <hi>Exchanged</hi> for, from the one place to the other.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the price of the Engliſh pound <hi>Exchanged at ſight,</hi> diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth from the ſame pound valued by any Prince or publicke authoritie, ordinarily <hi>foure</hi> or <hi>fiue pence</hi> in the pound.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the price of th'engliſh pound <hi>Exchanged</hi> for <hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance,</hi> differeth from the ſame pound deliuered, and taken for ſight, ordinarily <hi>fiue</hi> or <hi>ſix pence</hi> in the pound.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the price of the ſame pound taken and <hi>Exchanged</hi> for <hi>Double Vſance,</hi> differeth from the pound by <hi>Vſance,</hi> vi. or vii. <hi>pence:</hi> ſo that an Engliſh pound <hi>Exchanged</hi> by this laſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of time, differeth in price from a pound taken vp by the firſt difference of time, xii. or xiii <hi>pence</hi> in the ſayd pound.</p>
               <p>Many other diuerſities, as well of Times as of Money, be and may be practiſed &amp; exerciſed in this <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange:</hi> Whereof to diſcourſe perticularly, were too long and tedious: forſomuch as this briefe declaration of theſe diuerſities be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15000:11"/>recited, may ſuffiſe not onely for the perceiuing and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the ſame: but alſo for all other that be, or may be practiſed in the ſayd <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange,</hi> for as theſe three prices differ proportionally one from another, according to the rate and diſtance of time: ſo doe all other prices therof, according to the proportion of time they bee paſſed for.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> The manner of rayſing the valuation of Money in <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOraſmuch as the iuſt and lawfull valuation of Money can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not maintaine this ſubtill <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange,</hi> euerie peece of Gold, and great peece of Siluer, ſet forth &amp; cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in any Common-wealth, is alwaies of more valuation af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that it is currant Money in this foreſaide <hi>Exchange,</hi> by two pence, foure pence, or ſixe pence in a peece, more or leſſe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the quantity and ſubſtance it is of, then it is by the Princes, and publick authority of the Countrey where it was firſt coyned.</p>
               <p>Which pollicie in rayſing of Money, is cheefely practiſed of the Bankers of Antwerpe, to allure Merchants of all other parts to bring thither ready Money, and therefore make they the coynes of all other Countries, more woorth with them, then in any other Country els, although they be not ſo allowed and excepted by the authoritie of theyr Countrey. Yet being thus valued by them, they be made the common currant Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to buy and ſell all manner of wares &amp; Merchandizes there trafficked, and the way to paſſe and practiſe theyr <hi>Exchange</hi> with.</p>
               <p>And becauſe they will not haue the Princes Lawful Money to be the meane to buy &amp; ſell all things with, they compound in all their Contracts, Bargaines and <hi>Exchanges,</hi> to haue the payments made in this theyr Inuented Money, which they call, <hi>Currant Money in Merchandize:</hi> And furthermore, by this licentious libertie that they vſurpe in priſing, and valewing all Princes Money, they make many ſorts of Money currant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, which common Authority doth not permit nor allow to be payable nor currant in the Countrey. Whereby they haue greatly increaſed and aduanced the trade and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of <hi>Merchants</hi> in thoſe parts and Countryes: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15000:11"/>therewithall hath proceeded the greateſt occaſion, of the exceſſiue prices which raigneth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wares, Merchandizes, and commodities, in all Countryes at this day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> The difference betweene the Lawfull <hi>Exchange,</hi> and Merchandiſing <hi>Exchange.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN the <hi>Exchange</hi> which before is called tollerable and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Exchange,</hi> the price and valuation ſet foorth by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick authority, is chiefely to be conſidered and regarded in the Money <hi>Exchanged</hi> thereby, to the end that a iuſt &amp; equall payment, may bee made againe thereof to the Party that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuereth his Money by the ſayd <hi>Exchange.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for example, if the Ambaſſador of a Prince had neede of 100. li. Engliſh to be payd him at Antwerp, and would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer his 100. li. in London, to haue the iuſt value thereof payd him againe in Flemiſh Money, at his or the comming of his letter to Antwerp.</p>
               <p>Heere is to be conſidered onely, what and how much the Engliſh pound is worth Flemiſh, by the Princes valuation of thoſe parties, the valuation whereof is at the leaſt xxii .ſhillings and vi. pence Flemiſh, after which valuation the hundred pound Engliſh ſhall make Flemiſh 112. li. 10 .ſh. Likewiſe, if he would haue a 100. Crownes of the ſun, payd him in <hi>Paris</hi> in Fraunce, for the value thereof deliuered in <hi>London</hi> by the <hi>Exchange,</hi> forſomuch as it is knowne, that the French crowne is valued in England at vi .ſh, Engliſh; &amp; in Fraunce it is valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Prince at 50. ſous; now vi .ſh. in Enliſh after 2. ſous and a halfe for the Engliſh grot, amounteth to 45. ſous in the crowne, ſo that a hundred crownes amounteth to 4500. ſous in French, and after the French valuation of the crowne, they amount to 5000. ſous, ſo that for a hundred crownes at the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue thereof deliuered in England by this lawfull <hi>Exchange,</hi> he ought to receiue in Fraunce, 111. crownes, 5. ſous, as hee doth at Antwerp for his 100. li. a 112. li. 10. ſt. Flemiſh: and this <hi>Exchange</hi> may be made without the Merchants three di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities and <hi>diſtances of time,</hi> very well, truly, and iuſtly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe neither party ſeeketh to buy and ſell Money thereby, but to commute and <hi>Exchange</hi> it, according to the iuſt value giuen to the ſame, by the Princes and common authorities of both
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15000:12"/>Countryes. So that neither the Taker nor Deliuerer ſhall haue any more or leſſe, then that is due to them, although the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerer of the Money do tarry, or be contented to tarry 15. or 20. dayes for the receite of his Money, the Receiuor receiueth no domage nor hinderance thereby, but rather commoditie and profit, nor yet the Deliuerer, if hee haue his Money to ſerue his purpoſe at the time appointed, ſo that heere is no neceſſitie of intereſt to be payd to any partie for the forbearing of Money.</p>
               <p>And ſurely this was onely the vſe and cuſtome of the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change</hi> at the firſt beginning thereof, to the which if it were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored againe, the Princes Embaſſadors of England, lying in Fraunce and in other places ſhould not leeſe, 7. or 8. in the hundred, for two or three months ſpace, in taking vp of Mony for Parris, to be payd againe at Antwerp, and from thence at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange,</hi> to doe their Prince and Country ſeruice, but ſhould rather be gainers by the lawfull and honeſt <hi>Exchange,</hi> as reaſon and conſcience declareth they ſhould bee. And yet notwithſtanding might the <hi>Banker</hi> and <hi>Cambiador</hi> be allowed for his paines and labour, for the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and paying of the Money, ſomewhat after the olde man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Spaine and Italy, which is after the rate, of three in the hundred for the yeere, and ſo ſhould he not be euill payd ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, nor yet the Payer and Deliuerer of the Money by <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change</hi> ouer burdened and charged, as they be now a dayes eaten out of houſe and home by <hi>Merchandiſing Exchang,</hi> if onely this lawfull <hi>Exchange</hi> were reſtored againe, for the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Money from Country to Country.</p>
               <p>Contrariwiſe, in this corrupt and crafty <hi>Exchange,</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutation of Money, the ſayd publicke valuation of Money is altogether neglected, ſecluded, and put out of minde, and only the price and valuation, that Money hath giuen to it by meere chaunce in the ſame <hi>Exchange,</hi> conſidered and paſſed vpon: and ſo neither can equallity nor indifferency be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the payment againe of the Money, taken and deliuered by the ſame <hi>Exchange,</hi> but that one of the parties muſt be bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened thereby, nipped and oppreſſed, for that it is bought &amp; ſold at lower and higher prices then it ought to haue by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick authoritie, according to the pleaſure of <hi>Merchants</hi> ſeeking lucar and gaines thereby. As for example, if one in London would haue a hundred crownes paid him in Parris by that <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change,</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:15000:12"/>firſt, at his deliuering in London of his 100. crownes, he muſt compound &amp; agree with him he maketh his <hi>Exchange</hi> withall, how much Engliſh Money hee ſhall deliuer in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, for euery French-crowne to be payd in Parris againe: for the Princes valuation will not ſerue, but hee muſt agree vpon a new price of Engliſh Money for the ſaid crownes: ſo where it is worth in England by the Princes valuation but vj .ſhillings, the <hi>Exchanger</hi> will haue ſixe ſhillings foure pence, or ſix pence, or peraduenture a noble, according as the occaſion of <hi>Time</hi> ſerueth for euery crowne to be paid in Parris, and ſometimes more.</p>
               <p>So that, where by equitie and conſcience, which is knowne by the Princes and publicke valuation of the crowne, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerer of the Money in England, ſhould receiue for his hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred crownes deliuered in England, a hundred and eleuen crownes and fiue ſous at Parris, he now by this <hi>Merchants Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change,</hi> ſhall receiue at the moſt not aboue 105. crownes, or 102 crownes, and ſometime leſſe then the hundred crownes. So that by this one example, appeareth ſufficiently what a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence it is to paſſe Money by the Lawfull <hi>Exchange,</hi> which is ruled and ordered by the ſtable &amp; conſtant price giuen to Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney by publick Authoritie, and by this other fallible <hi>Exchange,</hi> depending onely vpon the alterable price of Money, giuen af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the inſtable affection of couetous Merchants.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> The firſt ſtanding <hi>Bankes</hi> and <hi>Pillars</hi> of <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange.</hi> And a Deſcription thereof.</head>
               <p>THE firſt &amp; principall piller of all, may <hi>Rome</hi> moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily be taken and reputed, where ſuch great rapine,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vſury</hi> first hatched in Rome.</note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varice, and other filthines if ſo in common vſe, that it is figured in the Scriptures by the Beaſt and Harlot, with vvhom all the Princes, Merchants, &amp; rich men of the Earth haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted abhomination, and of whom they haue learned the loue of Money, that is, Idolatry: Whoſe Antichriſtian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Gouernours, by reaſon of the Anates, and other great tributes exacted, ſpecially of the Eccleſiaſticall perſons of all other Realmes, inuented this Commutation and <hi>Exchange,</hi> as the moſt expedient and commodious meane for the conuey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their reuenewes vnto them; ſo that the holy Fathers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15000:13"/>firſt in the Babilonicall <hi>Rome,</hi> the erection of a ſtanding Banck for the Traffick and <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange,</hi> by which meanes it hath euer ſince beene in exerciſe, for the tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Money as a ware and <hi>Merchandize,</hi> by the miniſtery of <hi>Merchants,</hi> from all places of Chriſtendome to the Citty of Rome.<note place="margin">Rome,</note> Vnto the which in continuance, the ſayd <hi>Merchants</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo delighted with that trade, haue deuiſed to adioyne three other Citties for <hi>Standing Bancks,</hi> and Pillers of the ſame <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change,</hi> as <hi>Venice, Lyons,</hi> and <hi>Antwerpe:</hi> Which foure places, be therefore called <hi>Standing-Bancks,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Venice, Lyons, Antwerp.</note> becauſe the Exchangers and Bankers thereof, doe exerciſe the ſame <hi>Exchange</hi> publiquely, and haue their open ſhops for the ſame purpoſe at this day in all the ſaid Townes; and moreouer, they haue as it were ſome kind of Warrant, Liberties, and Preuiledges, from the Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Powers of the ſame Townes, for the more ſure and ſafe Traffick therein.</p>
               <p>By which Preuiledges, (at the leaſt in theſe other three Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties) vnder the pretence and couller to be lawfull <hi>Exchangers,</hi> and honeſt Merchants, all honeſt trade of Merchandize is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted throughout all the Townes &amp; Regions of <hi>Europe:</hi> but ſpecially in England, all manner of wares and Merchandiſes, &amp; other commodities of the Realme, be growne thereby to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſiue prices; from whence alſo ſpring daily more and more abuſes and abſurdities, in the Trades and manner of all ſorts of Occupiers throughout all Chriſtendome.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Diſcription of <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange.</hi>
                  </note>Therefore <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange,</hi> is an vnlawfull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutation of Money made betweene parties, vppon certaine ſubtill compacts &amp; conditions for the paſſing of Money from one Country to another, according to the priuate valuation giuen by <hi>Merchants</hi> and Banckars, to the coynes and Monies of all Princes and common Wealths; deuiſed and inuented of them, only for their priuate benefit, and gaine, to the confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all good order in <hi>Merchandiſing,</hi> and the corruption of all honeſt occupying and Traffick in any common Wealth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Three Practiſes, and fiue Abuſes hurtfull and pernicious to all Common-wealths by <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange.</hi>
               </head>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:15000:13"/>
               <p>FIrſt, Merchants doe make thereby all Princes coynes and Moneys, to be as wares and Merchandiſes, buying and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the ſame for more and leſſe price, as well as any other kind of ware and Merchandiſe they traffick in, contrary to the nature of Money, and alſo the Lawes and Ordinances of all Princes and Common-wealths, by whoſe authority onely, coynes of Money ought to haue theyr price and valuation, and that vnalterable, for the preſeruing of an <hi>Equitie</hi> in all thinges vendible in the Countries and Common-wealths.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Merchants do vſe by that meanes to ſerue theyr turnes of Money from one Country to another, therewith to buy wares and Merchandiſes: by which pollicie, they hinder Princes and Common-wealthes, of ſuch toles and cuſtoms as they ſhould pay to them, vpon theyr wares and commodities that they would bring and convey into their Dominions and Countries to doe theyr feate with, if this Merchandiſing of Money were not: whereby alſo many Merchants do coullour the conueying of ready Money out of the Realme of England. And ſpecially it is a great let, impediment &amp; hinderance to the bringing in of Bullyon into this Realme, which all forraine Merchants were wont to doe, when the commodities of the Realme were vented &amp; vttered at <hi>Callice,</hi> or at the <hi>Staple townes</hi> within England, before the two <hi>Societies</hi> of Engliſh Merchants began to vſurpe ſuch Liberties for the Traffick, as they pretend at this day to enioy by lawfull Authority.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Merchants at this day doe practiſe to buy and ſell onely according to the price and valuation that Money hath, by the diſorder of this <hi>Merchandiſing-Exchange:</hi> and doe omit and paſſe ouer the iuſt and lawfull valuation of Money giuen; and ſet foorth in euery Country by the Prince and common authority thereof; Money beeing the onely meane to preſerue a mediocritie and an <hi>equalitie</hi> in the prices of all things vendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, in any Countrey or Common-wealth, and ſo haue they beene the occaſion why the prices and eſtimation of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of wares and commodities be ſo exceſsiuely inhaunced &amp; riſen in the Realme of England at this day.</p>
               <p>¶ 1. Firſt, by the occaſion of this <hi>Exchange,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vſury.</note> many perſons in diuers places, before intangled and wrapped in &amp; with hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie burdens, byting, and <hi>inextricable Vſuries.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:15000:14"/>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, it cauſeth the Traffick, with the vſe &amp; cuſtome of borrowing and lending of Money in a Common-wealth, to be hard, deere, and ſcant, which is a very neceſſary and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient thing to be liberally, frankly, and freely vſed.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly, it giueth occaſion to all maner of Occupiers, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they follow no iuſt and lawfull trade of Merchandize, to ſet theyr prices of their Wares after ſuch ſort and rate, that theyr gaines thereby may paſſe and exceede, not onely <hi>ſix</hi> and <hi>eight</hi> in the hundred, but alſo <hi>twelue,</hi> for a ſmall time.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Fourthly, vnder the cullour therof, not only the <hi>Bankars</hi> of Antwerp, and Lyons, with ſuch like Vſurers, openly, and by profeſſion practiſing Vſury, doe exceede the Limits of all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and lawfull intereſt, in letting or lending out their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, but alſo all other couetous Perſons, hauing Money by them, by the example of theſe <hi>Exchaungers,</hi> either publickly, or priuily, either openly or ſecretly, ſeeke the meanes and wayes, to put out their Money for the like gaines, pretending and alledging for their excuſe, that they put and let out their Money, in company with theſe <hi>Exchanging Merchants</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen Vſurers, vpon common gaine.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Fiftly, many <hi>Merchants,</hi> eſpecially ſuch as haue growen to great wealth and riches, be and haue beene by this meanes allured and entiſed, to giue ouer and neglect all manner of honeſt trade of <hi>Merchandize,</hi> and buying and ſelling, whereby they haue beene and might be profitable and commodious to there common Wealth: and to followe this filthy, vnlawfull, and too farre exceeding gaine and lucar of practiſing wicked Vſurary, chopping and changing of Money, and all for the hope they conceiue thereby, to obtaine and get both a more abundant and certaine gaines, and that alſo with leſſe labor, charges, perrill and aduenture.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X. How</hi> &amp; by <hi>whom</hi> the practiſing of the <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange,</hi> is the Cauſe of all <hi>exceſſiue prices</hi> in Commodities &amp; things vendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: to the preuenting and peruerting of all lawfull <hi>Traffick</hi> and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly <hi>Dealing</hi> within the Realme and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth of England.</head>
               <p>THe neceſſity of conſeruing an equallity in contracts of buying and ſelling, and a fit meanes for the exportations, and importations, of things neceſſary and commodious
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15000:14"/>for a Common Wealth, hath cauſed all wiſe &amp; politick Rulers of Regions and Countries, to iudge the vſe of coyned Money; ſigned with ſome publick <hi>figures, notes,</hi> and <hi>carrects,</hi> to be the moſt conuenient thing that could be deuiſed. In like manner hath it beene iudged, and thought no leſſe expedient and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, by all ſuch wiſe and experienced Men, that the ſame coynes and Money ſhould haue their <hi>indication, valuation, price,</hi> and <hi>eſtimation,</hi> onely by publick Rulers &amp; common au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of euery Common Wealth: from the which no pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate Perſon, Order, or Societie in the ſame, may or ought to ſwarue or vary, nor alter, vnder capitall paine. Forſomuch as the ſayd publick valuation, is as it were the eſſentiall part, whereby any kinde of matter, ſubſtance, or mettall, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued and accepted for Money, and for a lawful meane to buy &amp; ſell withall, in euery well ordered Common Wealth. And whereas the valuation of this common, and lawfull meane of price, is not well knowen, or not worthily accepted, ſtraightly &amp; duly obſerued, of all manner of Perſons, Societies, and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, there doth experience teach, that thereof followeth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion and diſorder, with exceſſiue and immoderate prices in the commutations of all things Vendible in the Common Wealth.</p>
               <p>As for example, when a Prince or Ruler of any Country, doth decry and diſalow any kinde of coyne and Money, which he hath ſuffered before time to be currant, at a certaine price and valuation throughout his Realme, the ſame coyne im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly as it is ſo decried, leſeth the eſtimation it had before, and is of no value to buy any kinde of ware with, amongſt all the common people of the ſame Realme; ſo that few or none will receiue the ſayd Money for any manner of ware, though one would offer it at much lower price then it was before cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for: and if it chaunce any doe bargaine to take it, they will raiſe and inhance the price of the wares they vtter, much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the ordinary price thereof, &amp; all becauſe it lacketh their Princes and common valuation of their Country. In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner do the common people of all Countries, eſteeme forraine, ſtrange, and vnknowne coynes brought vnto them, not valued by the common authority of their Country, how fine and pure ſoeuer the matter or mettall of them be, onely (as is ſayd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) for lacking the publick valuation of the Country. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it is apparant, that the Princes and publick valuation of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15000:15"/>is of ſo great efficacy and authority, in euery ciuill Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Wealth, that not only it maketh it a meane to buy things withall, but alſo it preſerueth a moderation, equallity, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differency in the prices of all things, ſo bought and ſold be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene party and party. Therefore is the ſayd valuation ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and (as a man may ſay) religiouſly to be kept and obſerued of all manner of ſorts of perſons in a Common Wealth. And the Alterars &amp; Changers of the ſame by their priuate authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, are worthily to be reprehended and reproued, how crafti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſubtilly ſoeuer they doe it, for the manifold inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences they thereby bring into their Country: With a number of which, the Common Wealth of England, is ſore troubled at this day, through the frequent practiſing of <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange,</hi> by the two <hi>Societies</hi> of <hi>Merchants Staplerers</hi> and <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenturers</hi> of England, betweene their owne Country, and the Marting Townes of Flanders, with ſlights, crafts, and ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: continually thereby altering the price and valuation of their Princes coyne; by the occaſion whereof, all manner of wares and commodities only ſold in the Realme of England, be brought and grow to ſuch inordinate and exceſſiue prices, as they beare at this Day: for the proofe of the premiſſes, this reaſon may be firſt made.</p>
               <p>Afore this <hi>Merchandizing Exchange</hi> was practiſed by the Engliſh Merchants <hi>Staplers</hi> and <hi>Aduenturers,</hi> betweene the Marting-Townes of Flaunders, Brabant, &amp; their owne Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, in the trafficke of Merchandiſe to and fro, no perſon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained vpon any manner of Merchandize, or commoditie of the Realme, nor of forraine Realmes brought into England, did at any time grow or ariſe to inordinate or exceſsiue prices: yet were the commodities of the Realme abundantly &amp; plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully, yea, more liberally exported and tranſported into all forraine Countries, then at this day. But there were not in thoſe dayes ſo many forraine wares brought in againe into the Realme, as be at this day. For from the raigne of the famous King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, in whoſe dayes the trade of Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize began cheefely to be exerciſed in England, vnto the end of <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, which is the ſpace of aboue 150. yeeres, Acts of Parliament were prouided, thereby forcing all maner of men that occupied and fold the wares and commodities of the Realme to forraine Merchants, to raiſe and keepe vp the prices of them, and penalties layd vppon thoſe which went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15000:15"/>to diminiſh and bring downe the prices of them.</p>
               <p>And in all this ſpace of time, not onely <hi>Wooll</hi> and <hi>Felles,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Staples wont to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in England, and not beyond Seas.</note> were Staple wares at <hi>Callice,</hi> and other <hi>Staple-townes,</hi> in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and at length, <hi>Broad-clothes</hi> tranſported into Flaunders, and Brabant; but all other manner of commodities of the Realme, as <hi>Leather, Lead, Tinne, Butter,</hi> and <hi>Cheeſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Free tranſportation of home Commodities, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall for Traffick, &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiall for the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-Wealth.</note> were <hi>Staple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares,</hi> and <hi>freelie</hi> (onely paying the Kings cuſtome for them) carryed &amp; exported <hi>out of the Realme</hi> into all forraine Realmes. But ſithence theſe two Societies of Engliſh <hi>Marting-Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants,</hi> practiſing the <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange,</hi> haue made the exporting and tranſporting of the commodities and Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizes of the Realme, to the Staple of <hi>Callice,</hi> &amp; Marting-townes☞ of Brabant, a priuate trade to themſelues, the Princes of this Realme haue beene conſtrained to reſtraine and prohibite, not onely the going out of certaine of the aforeſaid commodities of the Realme; but alſo haue beene compelled to ſtudie and deuiſe meanes by Acts of Parliament, to bring &amp; keep downe the prices, as well of the commodities of the Realme: as of all forraine Realmes. Therfore it muſt needes be concluded, that <hi>Merchandizing Exchange,</hi> and the practiſing thereof, is the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of this great inconveniencie and Miſchiefe raigning in the Common-wealth of England. By the reaſon whereof, all things be growne to exceſſiue prices.</p>
               <p>Alſo, ſince theſe two afore-ſaide Companies of Engliſh Merchants vſurped theſe Liberties and Priuiledges to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, that the one of them ſhould tranſport only Staple wares to the Staple of <hi>Callice,</hi> and the other Broad-clothes,<note place="margin">Note, Staple-Townes beeing called Mart-Townes, began the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of Trades &amp; Townes in England.</note> with ſuch other Commodities, vnto the <hi>Marting-Townes</hi> of Brabant, the moſt part of all the good Townes of the Realme of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land haue decayed and come to ruine, which partly hath come to paſſe, by the reaſon that many kinde of Artificers, vvhich were wont to inhabite the ſaid Townes, maintaine and make th<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e proſperous by ſuch artificialls as they made there: by the meanes of theſe two fraternities of <hi>Marting-Merchants</hi> be vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtroyed &amp; conſumed, for that they were notable at length to liue by their arts and labours, theſe fore-ſaid Merchants de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſing and cauſing the like Artificials as the ſaid Artificers made in England, to be made in forraine Countries, and were by them brought and tranſported into England, and ſold better cheape ſome-what, &amp; lower priced then thoſe of Engliſh ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king might be aforded. Thorough which occaſion, the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15000:16"/>Artificers in continuance were worne out, becauſe none were brought vp vnder other, to follow their ſaid Art &amp; work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip, that they exerciſed, forſomuch as they percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that they ſhould not be able to liue by ſuch kind of labour in time to come; becauſe the forraine workmanſhip was more regarded, and ſooner bought then theirs. Partly alſo they haue beene the deſtruction, decay, and ruine of the ſaid Townes, by taking away the trade of the Staple from the ſaid Townes, for the vtterance of the commodities of the Realme, which for the moſt part of all the time,<note place="margin">Staple Townes alwaies within England, made the Realme full of Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficke.</note> from <hi>Edward</hi> the third, to the end of <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, were kept in good Townes of England, or at leaſt ſhipped from them when the Staple was kept at <hi>Callice,</hi> by the occaſion whereof, there was ſo great reſort of people vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſaid Townes, that thereby they were enriched, and daily proſpered and flouriſhed. Whereſince, for lacke of like reſort and trafficke, and the deſtruction of the foreſaid Artificers, they be altogethers ruinous and decayed, and neuer like to be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſo long as theſe Merchants enioy theyr vſurped liberties.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, ſince theſe two Societies of Engliſh Merchants, vſurped vnto them the priuate exportations of the commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities of the Realme,<note place="margin">The hindrance of bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in of Bullyon.</note> the liberall, vſuall, and daily bringing in of Bullyon into the Realme by forraine Merchants out of all forraine Realmes, to buy the commodities of England, hath decayed and ceaſed; and ſeuere and great puniſhments and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties be prouided by the Princes of ſuch forraine Realmes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all them which ſhall attempt the conueying of any ſuch things out of theyr Realmes into England: Where in times paſſed, they moſt gladly ſuffered and concented vnto it, for that it was openly knowne, to all Princes and Rulers of Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths in Chriſtendome, that what kinde of Merchant ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer,<note place="margin">Staples euer kept within England.</note> reſorted <hi>into England to the Staple-Townes,</hi> for the and carrying away of the commodities &amp; Merchandiſes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, were bound by the Acts and orders of the Realme, to pay for them at the ſaid Staples, in ready gold and filuer afore their departure from thence; as may appeare by diuers Acts made in diuers Kings dayes, from <hi>Edward</hi> the third, vnto the end of <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth: and therefore at that time were all Princes well contented, to ſuffer their Merchants to carry their coynes and Bullyon into England.</p>
               <p>Which manner of Traffick, continued betweene England and all other Realmes, till that theſe Merchants became to be
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15000:16"/>a priuate Society, and ſo vvithin a while after, compounded &amp; agreed with the Merchants of Holland, Zeland, Brabant, Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and other Countries there-abouts, which were the buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Staple-wares, to receiue their Money for ſuch Staple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares, as the ſayd Staplers ſold them at <hi>Callice,</hi> in Flemiſh Money, at the Marting Townes of their owne Countries, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, ſetting, and valuing the Engliſh pound, at a certaine ſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted price of Flemiſh Money, for euer thereafter to bee payed vnto them, after the ſaid price; which was a drift driuen of the ſayd Staplers of England, to bring to paſſe this <hi>Exchanging</hi> Traffick, to the intent they might make the returne of their Money, from thence into England by <hi>Merchandiſing Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change:</hi> whereby they made a reckoning, much more to their priuate gaines and lucar, then to be payed in ready Money at the Staples of <hi>Callice,</hi> or any place of England, according to the olde cuſtome, although that manner of payment was much more beneficiall, and commodious for the common Wealth of the whole Realme, which they paſſed not vppon, neither yet doe, ſo they may gaine and get Money.</p>
               <p>And thus the faire Lady <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange,</hi> enticed and allured the <hi>Merchants Aduenturers</hi> of England,<note place="margin">Staples called Mart Townes, <hi>a deceptio Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> to turne all Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick beyond Seas, to the ruine of England.</note> to procure themſelues in fraternitie, and to ſeeke meanes to plant their <hi>Marting Townes</hi> in a forraine Realme and Country, for the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terance of the commodities of the Realme, becauſe they might make their returne and imployments, from thence into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lang, by the reckoning of Money currant in the ſayd <hi>Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſing Exchange.</hi> And by this meanes, ceaſed and ended the franck and free bringing in of Money, &amp; Bullion into England by forraine and ſtrange <hi>Merchants,</hi> after the Engliſh <hi>Merchants</hi> had nuſſeled themſelues in the <hi>Marting Townes</hi> beyonde the Sea, ſo that now a dayes, no Money or Bullion is brought into England by <hi>Merchants,</hi> but ſecretly, and as it were, by ſtealth, and for the reſpect of priuate gaines and profite, which they finde thereby, after the reckoning they make thereof, by cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantnes of Money in their <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Item, when it pleaſed that famous Prince,<note place="margin">Henry <hi>the eight.</hi>
                  </note> King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, vpon good conſiderations and purpoſes, and for the great benefite of his people, and common Wealth, to aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and increaſe the valuation and price of his coyne and Money, throughout all his Realme, within a little proceſſe and countinuance of time after, it chanced by the malice and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15000:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>wickednes of men, ſuch a quantity of currupt, and droſſy coyne of Money, to bee brought into the Realme out of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine Countryes, by the Miniſtery of <hi>Merchants:</hi> (as it hath beene ſuppoſed, thought, and gathered by certaine cercum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances) which Money being currant, as well as the true and lawfull Money, amongſt all manner of perſons within the Realme, by the reaſon of the likenes of the faſhion, and forme that it had with the true and lawfull Money, cauſed many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences to riſe therby at length, to the whole Common Wealth: for ſuch a meruailous deſire and haſtynes, entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all kinde of Occupiers, by the lothſomnes and hatred they conceiued of the ſayd Droſſe coyne, to beſtow it vppon one thing or other, that thereupon beganne to grow ſome diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of prices in all wares and commodities, ſold in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: which being firſt perceiued by the Graue, and Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Gouernors of the Realme, in the raigne of bleſſed King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the ſixt, they conſulted together for the deuiſing of ſome wayes to be taken, to auoyde the ſaid diſorder ſo begunne and ſprung. And the beſt meanes for that purpoſe was thought by their wiſdomes, to be the deminiſhing, of all the white cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant coyne and Money of the Realme: intending by that meanes at the length, to haue vtterly baniſhed from thence all ſuch counterfeited coyne, taking leiſure withall ſtudy &amp; care, to doe it with as much eaſe, and as little loſſe to euery State &amp; condition as could be deuiſed. But before this their godly and moſt lawdable purpoſe, could be brought to effect, when it was yet but in talke and conſultation, and onely a rumor bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ſpred abroade that ſuch a decry of Money ſhould be; The <hi>Merchants Aduenturers</hi> prepared withall ſpeed poſſible,<note place="margin">The <hi>Merchants Aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turers,</hi> priuate ſhift to preuent the Princes pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe for the common good.</note> Armour and defence againſt the loſſe, which they feared their State ſhould fall into thereby, when indeede euery perſon of the Realme, ought to haue borne with a very good will the ſayd loſſe, for the redreſſing of the ſayd diſorder ſo ſprung vp in the Realme, in the prices of all things, bought and ſold be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene party and party: according as the prudent and wiſe Counſellors of the Kings Maieſty, had deuiſed and purpoſed to haue brought to paſſe, and as the reſt of all States of the ☞Realme would haue yeelded vnto: if the <hi>Merchants Aduentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers,</hi> had beene deſtitute of their <hi>Exchange.</hi> But greedy lucar and priuate gaine, coulde not ſuffer their couetous harts to beare any little loſſe at that preſent, though it ſhould in the end
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15000:17"/>haue turned to the common benefit of all the Realme. And ſo forſooth without further helpe, they vſed the pollicy of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſing Exchange,</hi> their practiſe wherein was as it were, to diſualue and decry the price, of the Engliſh pound in currant Money by the ſame <hi>Exchange:</hi> for the paſſing of Money ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by betweene England, and their <hi>Marting-Townes.</hi> Which pound had beene currant amongſt them, two and fro in the ſayd <hi>Exchange,</hi> vntill that time, betweene 26 .ſh. and 30 .ſh. Fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh, but then ſodainely they decried and diſualued it to 16. and 17 .ſh. Flemiſh; and at length, to 13 .ſh. Flemiſh, before the alteration of the coyne was proclaimed: by the which oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, the prices of all forraine wares and <hi>Merchandizes,</hi> roſe exceſſiuely in England, as of neceſſity they muſt, for the leſſe Flemiſh Money is allowed for the Engliſh pound at the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting-Townes,</hi> at the other ſide the Sea in their foureſayd <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change,</hi> the dearer and the higher prices muſt all that Country wares beare, bought there to bee tranſported into England, which for the reſpect of the baſe price of th'engliſh Money, muſt needes be ſold after the like rate in England. For whereas before vntill that time, the Engliſh pound had beene worth at the ſayd <hi>Marting-Townes,</hi> at leaſt, 26. ſſ. Flemiſh, then by this abaſing of the <hi>Exchange,</hi> 26. ſſ. Flemiſh was brought to bee worth at the end, 40. ſſ. Engliſh, becauſe the ſayd Engliſh pound was no more in value, but 13. ſſ. Flemiſh, in their <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſing Exchange,</hi> by which meanes the thing that coſt but 13 .ſh. Flemiſh, was ſold betweene 20, and 26. ſſ. Engliſh, in England: which manners of Sales, muſt needes cauſe all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Flemiſh wares to beare exceſſiue and inordinate prices there, which immoderate prices of ſtrange and forraine wares, were ſufficient cauſe to be alledged, why all the commodities of England, did firſt ariſe to ſuch prices as they doe ſtill beare, euen at this day: becauſe ſo great a quantity, of the ſayd Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders wares were brought thether, and bee in ſo great vſe, ſo much bought and ſpent, of all manner of ſorts of perſons in England.</p>
               <p>Yet notwithſtanding, the ſaid Flemiſh wares were not the next and principall cauſe, that the Engliſh commodities did ſo riſe and exceed in price: but rather the two Companies of Engliſh Merchants, the <hi>Staplers</hi> &amp; <hi>Aduenturers,</hi> for they made ſo gainefull reckoning at their Marting-Townes, by returning home theyr Money by <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange,</hi> that they paſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15000:18"/>not what price they gaue and paid for the commodities of the Realme in England; for the <hi>Staplers</hi> made aboue 28. ſs. Flemiſh of euery pound Engliſh they ſolde theyr wares and Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizes ☞ for, by an old compoſition taken betweene them and the Merchants of thoſe parts, by the which manner of reckoning, they got aboue 60. in the hundred in England.</p>
               <p>The like reckonings made the <hi>Merchants Aduenturers,</hi> by the ſales of theyr commodities, although theyr gaines were not ſo certaine, becauſe they had no ſuch compoſition with the Merchants of thoſe parts, as the <hi>Staplers</hi> had. Yet ſold they after ſuch rate, that they made of euery Engliſh pound, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene 26. and 28 .ſhillings Flemiſh, all the while the <hi>Exchange</hi> came from thence,<note place="margin">Admirable Vſury, after the rate of 400. pound, or 500. pound, made of 100. pound in one yeere.</note> betweene 16. and 18 .ſh. for the Engliſh pound. And ſo amounteth theyr gaines to aboue 50. and 60. in the 100. for a Moneths ſpace, or at the moſt, for the ſpace of one Mart, making and returning home theyr Money by their <hi>Exchange.</hi> During the time of which <hi>Exchange,</hi> there was ſuch a ſpeedy and quicke trafficke betweene England and the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting-Townes, and all for the loue of this lucar &amp; great gaines, that no commoditie in England tranſportable for thoſe parts, could lye by them vnbought. And this meanes and practiſe of the two Companies of Merchants, in following the Trafficke &amp; <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange,</hi> was the principall cauſe, why both forraine wares, and Engliſh, grew to ſuch exceſsiue prices in England. For when all other ſorts and conditions of perſons of the Realme, perceiued, that the bettering and amending of the ☞ coine of Mony of the Realme, was nothing eſteemed amongſt the Merchants, but rather leſſe regarded, as though it had bin leſſe in value then it was before, forſomuch as they daily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed the price of the wares they brought from the Marting-Townes to be ſold in England: All other States likewiſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne to paſſe and ſet nothing by it, and ſo rather couited to beſtow it raſhly and vnaduiſedly in one thing or other, what price ſo euer things did beare, then diſcreetly and warily to foreſee and looke afore-hand, how they might beſtow it, for the bringing downe of the immoderate prices that euerything was growne vnto, becauſe they were perſwaded, that the ſaid Engliſh coyne, was no more worth then the <hi>Exchanging Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants</hi> valued it at. In ſo much, that the Clothiers which came to <hi>Blackwell-hall,</hi> ſet theyr pices on their Clothes, according ☞ as they learned of the Merchants the price of Money came
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15000:18"/>from the <hi>Marting-Townes</hi> in their <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange</hi> into England, and not according to the valuation thereof giuen &amp; proclaimed by their Prince.<note place="margin">Merchants gouerne the Common-wealth.</note> So that Merchants brought all men to follow theyr bow, as concerning the eſtimation of Engliſh Money, where they in the meane ſeaſon, paſſed not what they gaue in England for the Commodities thereof, though they ſold them to no profit at the Marts, becauſe the returning of the Money from the Marting-townes by theyr <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange,</hi> was ſo profitable and gainefull vnto them, during this baſe and low price of <hi>Exchange.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Likewiſe, whereas the Queenes Maieſtie,<note place="margin">Elizabeth.</note> by the aduice of her prudent and graue Counſellers, mooued with great loue, zeale and pitty towards all ſtates of perſons, but ſpecially to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the poorer ſort, oppreſſed and burthened with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsiue prices of all things vendible within her Graces realme, which ſprung and roſe (as the common fame went) by the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of the Droſſy and monſtrous Baſe-Money, currant and ſet forth, or at the leaſt way, permitted to be currant and ſet foorth, by her Graces predeceſſors throughout the Realme: like a moſt godly and louing Princeſſe, hath taken away and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed, all the ſaid courſe and Droſſy Money &amp; coyne, and for it reſtored as fine ſiluer coyne, as euer was currant in the Realme before, or rather finer; hoping, meaning, and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thereby, to haue taken away there-with, the corrupneſſe and droſſines of prices, which likewiſe all thinges ſold in her Maieſties Realme at the time was corrupted with: As with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt (if no ſubtill pollicie had come betweene, to haue letted and ſtopped her Graces wholeſome purpoſe therein) it would haue effected. For ſome likelihood thereof began a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle while to appeare, by the falling of the prices of victuall at the Markets, when it was firſt noiſed and bruted abroade, that by a certaine day appointed and limited, no Money but ſuch as was of fine Siluer, or Gold, ſet forth by her Maieſty, or by her Graces Predeceſſors, ſhould be paiable or currant there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, within the Realme: and that all the droſſy coyne, ſhould be brought to her Mint of London, where euery man ſhould receiue for the ſame pure and fine Siluer Money of her Graces coyne: whereat all perſons much reioyced, although for the preſent euery ſtate of the Realme knew they ſhould receiue a loſſe thereby. Yet the conſideration of the benefit that was to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15000:19"/>a good will. But heere blind couetouſneſſe, with greedy gaine and lucar raigning in the <hi>Marting-Merchants,</hi> ſtirred vp theyr wits to practiſe their old ſubtill pollicie for the ſauing of theyr ſtate from loſſe, which was to bring downe and abaſe the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh pound in their <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange,</hi> for the returning home of theyr Money into England from their <hi>Marting-townes</hi> at the other ſide the Sea; and as they did before, in the bleſſed time of King <hi>Edward,</hi> ſo now at the firſt bruite and rumour of this Queenes moſt noble and euer praiſeable enterpriſe, they cauſed the price of her pound of Money to be valued in theyr <hi>Exchange</hi> but at 16. and 17. ſs. Flemiſh: by which occaſion, as it came to paſſe before at other reformations of Monies, the prices of all thoſe Countrey commodities, and alſo of all other forraine Nations and Countries, did not onely keepe theyr old exceſſiue and deere prices in England, but did rather en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and waxe higher, and ſo did likewiſe the commodities of the Realme follow after, not onely becauſe forraine wares did ſo, but ſpecially for the haſtines men made to beſtow their Money vpon them, by the examples of the <hi>Merchants Aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turers,</hi> who ſpared not to buy all manner of wares tranſporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble beyond the Sea, at what price ſoeuer was demaunded for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for that this returning home of Money by <hi>Exchange,</hi> made them great gayners, and would be a way &amp; meane, if the worſt fell, to keepe and ſaue them from all loſſe and danger in the fall of the Money, which all other ſtates and conditions hauing theyr traffick within the Realme, looked to haue ſuſtained and borne by the reformation of the ſaid Money, which theſe <hi>Merchants Aduenturers</hi> did prouide to auoyde, through this theyr peculier traffick and practiſe, by toſſing and turning their Money, betweene England and their <hi>Marting-Townes,</hi> by the ſayd <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For although the commodities of the Realme, which they tranſported to the <hi>Marts,</hi> roſe from 4. li. to 6. li. and 7. li. Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, yet might they ſell them at the <hi>Marts,</hi> as good cheape as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they did, and be greater gainers then in times paſt. For ſo much, as though cuſtomably they did make afore times 30. &amp; 34. ſs. Flemiſh of a pound Engliſh in theyr ſales, after which rate, they made 6. and 7. pound, 8. ſs. Flemiſh, of 4. li. Engliſh, and ſo 150. pound, and 160. li. Flemiſh, of a 100. li. Engliſh, yet becauſe they returned theyr Money by <hi>Exchange</hi> at that time after 28. ſs. and 30. ſs. or 32. ſs. Flemiſh for the Engliſh
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15000:19"/>pound, theyr gaines paſſed not aboue 13. in the hundred. Where now ſelling their commodities at the ſaid prices of 6. &amp; 7. li. Flemiſh, though they paid alſo for them ſo much in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land of Engliſh Money, (after which reckoning they did or do make of 100. li. Engliſh, but 100. Flemiſh) yet returning home their Money, after this reckoning and low <hi>Exchange</hi> of 16. and 17. ſs. Flemiſh for the Engliſh pound, they got betweene 17. &amp; 25. in the hundred, notwithſtanding they ſold not vnder 24. &amp; 26. ſs. Flemiſh for the pound Engliſh during the ſaid lowe <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change:</hi> after which rate, although they made but 120. &amp; 130. li. Flemiſh of their 100. li. Engliſh, yet made they in England at the returne of their Money, by the foreſaid low <hi>Exchange,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue 150. and 160. li. Engliſh of their 100. li. tranſported firſt from thence to the Marts. By which manner of reckoning, ☜ theyr gaines roſe to aboue 50. and 60. in the 100. for the ſpace of one Mart. And ſo by this policy of <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange,</hi> Merchants Aduenturers haue not only ſaued themſelues at all falls of Mony paſſed in England, &amp; haue hindred the Queenes Maieſties purpoſe,<note place="margin">Note.</note> for the bringing downe of the exceſſiue pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of things, in the vtter aboliſhing of all the droſſy &amp; corrupt Money in the Realme: but there-withall, they haue beene e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore the occaſion and Authors of the diſorder, and of the rayſing of all manner of wares and commodities in the Realme more and more, to ſuch exceſſiue and inordinate price, as ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they haue borne or doe beare at this day; neither is there any other kinde of State or Perſons in the Realme, that eyther could haue deuiſed, or els that went about to fruſtrate her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties purpoſes, in reducing all the baſe coynes to ſo pure or fine ſubſtance or matter, but onely theſe <hi>Merchants Aduentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers,</hi> by the practiſe of their <hi>fraudulent Exchange:</hi> for all other maner of perſons of the Realme, would gladly haue borne the loſſe of the Money, according to the Queenes Maieſties mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, becauſe they perceiued, that they ſhould thereby there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ſaue more for the buying of things at moderate and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable prices, then they ſhould loſe by the reformation of the coyne; for the cauſe beeing taken away of thoſe exceſſiue pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces (which was as all men ſaide, the droſſy and baſe coyne and Money of the Realme) the effect which proceedeth thereof, muſt needs alſo haue ceaſed and vaniſhed away. But ſeeing it hath not ſo come to paſſe, men muſt needes ſay and confeſſe, that ſome other ſubtiltie and policie, beſides the foreſaid droſſy
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15000:20"/>coyne,<note place="margin">Merchandiſing Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change.</note> hath cauſed this inordinate prices, which is <hi>Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſing Exchange;</hi> practiſed by <hi>Merchants Aduenturers,</hi> as is heretofore proued.</p>
               <p>ITEM, the ſame practiſing of <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange,</hi> is the meanes whereby all things doth continew deere, and at high prices ſtill in England: for like as is before declared, the <hi>Merchants Aduenturers,</hi> for their owne priuate lucar &amp; gaine, by the pollicy thereof, cauſed all things in the Realme to riſe to immoderate and exceſſiue prices: altering the valuation of the Engliſh pound, without reaſon or equity, by diſualuing, and bringing downe the prices thereof, farre vnder the value it ought to haue had in the ſayd <hi>Exchange:</hi> which pollicy they inuented, at the fall of the Money, to preuent the loſſe their State and Company ſhould haue receiued thereby.</p>
               <p>So after the fall was proclaimed in England, for the loue of the like priuate gaines and lucar which they had taſted of ſo ſweetely at the ſame time, euer ſince they haue kept the price vnder the ſumme of Money it ought to bee worth in the ſame <hi>Exchange,</hi> and thus paſſing and returning their Money in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to England vniuſtly and without equity, they ſtay all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of wares and commodities, at the vnreaſonable and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſiue prices they firſt brought them to, or rather doe raiſe them higher.</p>
               <p>For neuer ſince the Queenes Maieſtie, reduced all the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt coyne of the Realme to pure and fine Siluer, the price of the Engliſh pound hath come from the <hi>Marting-Townes</hi> into England, aboue 22. ſſ. 2. pence Flemiſh, at Vſance by the ſayd <hi>Exchange,</hi> where before till the firſt fall was noiſed in England, the coyne being moſt droſſy and corrupt, the price of the ſayd pound came from thence betweene, 26. and 28. ſſ. Flemiſh. To the which price the ſayd <hi>Merchants,</hi> ſhould doe their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour to bring it againe, rather then as they doe, keepe it at ſo vile a price, and farre vnder the price that it is eſteemed, and valued to be worth, in valued Money of that Country, ſet foorth by the Prince thereof, foraſmuch as all the Money of the Realme,<note place="margin">Mark well the vſe and aduantage which the <hi>Marchants Aduenturers,</hi> make of their ſpeciall <hi>Mart Townes,</hi> beyond the Seas, to the good of their Country.</note> is now ſo fine and pure. But greedy lucar hath no reaſon, which cauſeth that both the <hi>Merchants Aduenturers</hi> of England, and alſo the <hi>Merchants</hi> of the <hi>Marting-Townes,</hi> doe (as it were) by a conſpiracy betweene them, keepe the value of the Engliſh pound, at ſo vniuſt and vile price in their <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſing Exchange;</hi> for by reaſon thereof, doe the <hi>Merchants</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:15000:20"/>of thoſe parts ſell there wares to Engliſh <hi>Merchants,</hi> for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailous much more gaines, then euer they did before, and buy the commodities of England againe of them as good cheape, as euer they did at any time before: likewiſe the ſayd <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants</hi> of England, gaine and get much more then euery they did, whether they make imployments of their Money home in wares, or in Money by <hi>Exchange</hi> from the <hi>Marting-Townes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore it appeareth, that as this baſe, vile, and low price of the Engliſh pound, in their <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange,</hi> did raiſe at the firſt, all manner of wares and commodities, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate &amp; exceſſiue prices in England: ſo by the ſame <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants,</hi> hauing gathered ſo ſweete and pleaſant gaines, doe they ſtay and keepe them at thoſe ſayd immoderate, and exceſſiue prices, from the which there will no way be found to remoue them, ſo long as the <hi>Merchants</hi> may liberally at their pleaſure, vnder-price the Queenes Maieſties coyne of England, in their <hi>Exchange:</hi> and ſo trade and Traffick therewith, betweene Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and the ſayd <hi>Marting-Townes,</hi> becauſe of the great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie, gaine, and profit the <hi>Merchants</hi> of both Countries receiue by the ſame.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, the Queenes Maieſtie of England, receiueth great loſſe and dammage at the <hi>Merchants</hi> hands, by taking or prouiding Money of them by this their <hi>Merchandiſing Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change,</hi> according as they practiſe it now a dayes: for where the <hi>Merchants Aduenturers,</hi> and <hi>Staplers</hi> of England, eſteeme the Engliſh pound in their <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange,</hi> not aboue 22. ſſ. 6. pence Flemiſh, from London to Antwerp, at <hi>Vſance,</hi> yet is not that the true and iuſt valuation it ought to haue in currant Money of the ſayd <hi>Exchange,</hi> forſomuch as by the publick valuation of that Country Money, proclaymed by the commandement of the Prince, anno. 1559. the Engliſh pound of Money is eſteemed to be worth, of the ſame valued Money, 22. ſſ. 6. pence Flemiſh at leaſt, which valewed Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney is better by 6. pence, and 12. pence in a pound, then the currant Money by <hi>Exchange.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So then, when one deliuereth Money in London by <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſing Exchange,</hi> to be payd againe at Antwerp, <hi>at ſight,</hi> he ought to receiue there for his Engliſh pound of Money, at the leaſt, 23. ſſ. Flemiſh, of this <hi>Exchanging</hi> Money, and after the Order of <hi>Merchants,</hi> in the ſayd <hi>Exchange,</hi> if it be deliuered
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15000:21"/>for <hi>Vſance,</hi> he ought to receiue 23. .ſh 6. pence Flemiſh.</p>
               <p>Neither can the <hi>Merchants</hi> giue any good reaſon, why the price of the Engliſh pound in their <hi>Exchange,</hi> ſhould be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at this day but at 22 .ſh. 6. pence, ſeeing it is no leſſe worth in the valued Money of the ſayd Country.</p>
               <p>For after their olde Order of their <hi>Exchange,</hi> when the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh pound was valued in thoſe parties to bee worth 26 .ſh. 8. pence Flemiſh of the Princes Money, the ſayd pound in cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt Money of that <hi>Exchange,</hi> was worth 28 .ſh. ſo that then their was 4. Grotes of <hi>Exchanging</hi> Money allowed more to the Engliſh pound at the leaſt, then of valued Money, yea moſt commonly it came from thence into England, by their <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change</hi> at 30 .ſh. Flemiſh and ſomtime at 34 .ſh. of the ſayd Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, &amp; from hence it went at a more and higher price in their ſayd <hi>Exchange.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore according to the proportion of the prices of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney then, and now at this day: the price of the Engliſh pound from hence ought not to bee vnder 23 .ſh. 10. pence, &amp; from hence at 24 .ſh. 4. pence, for from hence by the Order of <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change,</hi> vnto the <hi>Marting-Townes,</hi> the price of the ſayd pound is higher and more worth, then from thence hether commonly, by 6. pence Flemiſh.</p>
               <p>Wherefore if truth and equity were vſed in this <hi>Merchandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Exchange,</hi> or if the foreſayd Engliſh <hi>Merchants</hi> frequented the <hi>Marting-Townes</hi> beyond the Sea, for the preferment of the Common Wealth of their Country, and not rather altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ☞ for their owne priuate gaines and lucar, they would neuer maintaine this piraticall <hi>Exchange,</hi> that they practiſe now a dayes, eſteeming the Engliſh pound to be leſſe worth of their <hi>Exchanging</hi> Money, then the Prince alloweth it to be worth of his valued Money, which was neuer ſeene before theſe dayes.</p>
               <p>For ſeeing their <hi>Exchanging</hi> Money is worſe by 6. pence &amp; 12. pence in a pound, then the Princes valued Money, why ſhould not more thereof bee giuen and allowed for the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh pound, then of valued Money according as it hath beene accuſtomed, to bee euer heere before when the Prince of that Country allowed 26 .ſh. 8. pence of his valued Money for the Engliſh pound.</p>
               <p>Therefore that the Queenes Maieſtie, might be exonerated of ſo great loſſe, when her affaires doe require the foreſayd
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15000:21"/>meane to prouide Money, and to the end ſome way of refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, might alſo be prouided for the redreſſing of the exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue prices, that ſpecially all forraine wares be ſold for in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land: the foreſayd <hi>Merchants Staplers</hi> and <hi>Aduenturers,</hi> would bee by ſome order compelled to bring the Engliſh pound, to this aforeſayd iuſt price &amp; valuation, it ought to haue in their vniuſt and polling <hi>Exchange,</hi> &amp; then ſhall they bring the Sales of their commodities, at the <hi>Marting Townes</hi> to be ſold at 26. and 27. ſſ. Flemiſh, and vpwards for the Engliſh pound: for the Sales of their wares muſt bee 2 .ſh. in a pound aboue the price it hath in their <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange,</hi> or els ſhall they make no reckoning to liue by.</p>
               <p>And ſo after this reckoning, raiſing the price of their <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change,</hi> ſhall they be able to ſell in England, and afford all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine commodities, 25. in the hundred better cheape, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the price they ſell them now a dayes: which reckoning ſhall induce ſome manner of reformation, in the diſordinate prices which all wares beare at this day, to the great eaſe of all the Common Wealth.</p>
               <p>After the ſame ſort, when the ſayd <hi>Marting-Merchants</hi> ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture into Spaine, although they can deuiſe no ſuch way and meanes to practiſe their <hi>Exchange</hi> thether, as they doe to there <hi>Marting-Townes,</hi> yet by the example thereof, they occupy in that Country as ſubtill practiſe, and as iniurious, and hurtfull to the Common Wealth of their Country, as their <hi>Exchange.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For when they beſtow xx. Nobles in the commodities of England, to be tranſported into Spaine, at the comming the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther withall, they make not their reckoning to ſell their wares, to make their Engliſh Money good againe in Spaniſh Money, that is, to make of euery Engliſh Noble 15. <hi>Rialls</hi> of plate, and of euery 5 .ſh. Engliſh. 11. <hi>Rialls,</hi> or a ſingle Ducate of Spaine, which were to make of euery pounds worth of Engliſh wares, 4. Ducates in Spaniſh Money: but they make their reckoning to ſel their wares there, as the Ducates were valued in England, when the coyne and Money of England was moſt baſe and droſſy, after the reckoning they make of an Engliſh Noble, but. 11. <hi>Rialls</hi> or a ſingle Ducate in Spaine.</p>
               <p>So where they ſhould ſell the 20. Nobles Engliſh, for 26. or 27. Ducats Spaniſh, if they were profitable <hi>Merchants</hi> for their Country, with ſome gaines towards their charges, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent themſelues now a dayes, rather then faile, to make of the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15000:22"/>20. Nobles Engliſh, but 20. Ducats Spaniſh, and ſo turne the matter cleane contrary, deuiſing afore-hand at their retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning home into England, to make by the Sales of ſuch Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh wares as they bring into England, not onely 20. Nobles Engliſh, of 20. Ducats Spaniſh, but within theſe few yeeres they haue priced Spaniſh wares after ſuch ſort, that they haue ☞ made of euery Spaniſh ſingle Ducate, betweene 8. and 10 .ſh. Engliſh.</p>
               <p>Which vnreaſonable reckoning they were moſt diligent to make, when the Engliſh pound was moſt vily priced in their <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange:</hi> and that was alwayes at ſuch time as when either the Queenes Maieſtie that now is, or any of her ☞ prodeceſſors: were moſt ſtudious by the aboliſhing of the ſayd droſſy and baſe coyne then currant, to haue brought downe the exceſſiue prices by their ſubtilty, raiſed vpon all things in England.</p>
               <p>For at ſuch times, the ſaid <hi>Marting Merchants</hi> haue alwayes thought beſt and moſt fitteſt to take occaſion to raiſe, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haunce the prices of all manner of things in their owne Country, to the entent thereby to decline and auoyde the loſſe that ſhould be borne by the reformation of the coyne &amp; Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and therewithall did they venture moſt buſily, their owne Country commodities into Spaine, in greater number then euer they were wount to doe before, and all becauſe of this new manner of reckoning, to make of euery Spaniſh Ducate 8. or 10 .ſh. Engliſh, in the Sales of thoſe Country wares.</p>
               <p>Through which occaſion, they haue alſo raiſed the commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities of that Country, to double and treble the price that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they were wont to be ſold for in Spaine: inſomuch, that the wiſe and diſcreete men of that Country, wiſh that the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Merchants</hi> might be kept from the trade of that Country, two or three yeeres together,<note place="margin">Note.</note> for then they ſay that the Wines of thoſe Partes, would not bee much more worth then the caske they be put in: And ſo likewiſe of Oyles, and other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities thereof which now be vnreaſonable deere: and yet doe they ſell their owne Country commodities in that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, not only as baſely and low priced as euer they did:<note place="margin">Note.</note> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo haue brought them to bee in no regarde or eſtimation throughout all the country, where they haue brought all thoſe Country wares to bee ſold in England, for thrice as much as a foretimes they were wount to be ſold in England, which be
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15000:22"/>vnreaſonable and exceſſiue prices.</p>
               <p>Yet can they not well ſell them vnder thoſe prices to be any gayners, they leeſe ſo much in the Sales of their owne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities which they ſell in thoſe parts, although they needed not to doe ſo, if they kept any <hi>Merchantlike</hi> Order in the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting of their commodities into thoſe parts: and in the Sales thereof at their comming thether, as other <hi>Merchants</hi> of the Realme haue done in times paſt, when they made euer recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to make in the Sales of their commodities in that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, 15. Rialls of plate of euery Engliſh Nobles worth of ware they brought thether, which gaines is ſufficient towards the charges.</p>
               <p>So might wiſe and diſcreete <hi>Merchants</hi> doe now at this day, as well as they which were wiſe in times paſt did; for the commodities of England, be as neceſſary and commodious for the Country at this day as euer they were before, and therfore would they giue for them<note n="*" place="margin">This Treatiſe was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten about the time of the Colloquy of Bruges, which was holden in aunis, 1564. et 1565.</note> as much Money as euer they did, whereof I <hi>poore</hi> and <hi>plaine</hi> WRITER of this <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> haue had good experience, <hi>euen in theſe dayes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>An</hi> Abridgement <hi>of the ſpeciall Inconueniences to</hi> this Realme of England, handled in the foreſayd tenth Chapter.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, that from tranſporting of the <hi>Store,</hi> and tranſlating of the <hi>Staples</hi> (ſometimes held at <hi>Callice</hi> and other <hi>good Townes</hi> in <hi>England</hi>) to priuat <hi>Mart-Townes</hi> in <hi>Forraine Countries,</hi> hath proceeded the principall occaſion of the ruine and decay of moſt of the <hi>Ports, Hauens, Townes,</hi> and <hi>Citties</hi> of this Realme, &amp; the ouerthrow of ſundry Artificers and Trades dwelling within them, moſt neceſſary to haue beene main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained for the generall good of the Common-Wealth, and ſpeciall reliefe of the poore.</p>
               <p>Secondly, That <hi>Merchants</hi> by the Vnderpricing of the coyne of this Realme in there <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange,</hi> at their priuat <hi>Mart-Townes,</hi> haue beene the impediment, that neither the Queenes Maieſtie, nor her Predeceſſors, could bring to effect the thing which they went about, by reforming and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fining the droſſy and lothſome coyne, and Money currant in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15000:23"/>the Realme.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the ſayd <hi>Merchants,</hi> by the practiſing of their <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſing Exchange,</hi> were the originall cauſe why all manner of wares, <hi>Merchandizes,</hi> and commodities, as well of the Realme of England, as of all other forraine Realmes, riſe to huge, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate, and exceſſiue prices.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, that all the excellent and neceſſary commodities of England, bee vnprofitably exported and tranſported into forraine Countries at this day, forſomuch as by the occaſion of their <hi>Merchandiſing Exchange,</hi> they bee better cheape ſolde abroade, then they coſt in England; to the great diſorder, and hinderance of the Common-Wealth.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, the Queenes Maieſtie is greatly defrauded by the ſayd <hi>Exchange,</hi> when her Maieſties affaires doe conſtraine her to prouide Money by that meanes at the foreſayd <hi>Merchants</hi> hands, (contrary to the truth and valution of her owne coyne) and ſo likewiſe be her Ambaſſadors, ſent in her Maieſties af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires and meſſages into any forraine Realme, when ſoeuer they haue neede to prouide Money by the ſayd <hi>Exchange.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixtly, by the practiſing of the ſayd <hi>Exchange,</hi> all manner of Gold and Siluer is continually conuaied, carried, and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported out of the Realme, and is the let and impediment, why neither Bullyon of Gold or Siluer, is ſo liberally and freely brought into the ſame as in times paſt it hath beene.</p>
               <p>Seauenthly &amp; laſtly, the ſayd <hi>Exchange</hi> cauſeth, through the vile, baſe, and vntrue valuation the foreſayd <hi>Merchants</hi> keepe the Engliſh pound at in their foreſayd <hi>Exchange,</hi> being ſo farre vnder the price it ought to haue; that theſe immoderate and exceſſiue prices, which they haue brought all things to be ſold at in England, cannot be diminiſhed, brought downe, or mitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated, to moderate, reaſonable, and indefferent prices.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:15000:23"/>
               <head>A generall Concluſion.</head>
               <p>THis <hi>Treatiſe</hi> thus ended, hath for warrant and Credite theſe foure Circumstances: probability of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> plaines of <hi>Stile,</hi> ſpeciall <hi>Experience,</hi> and <hi>Time</hi> of writing. From whence this <hi>Concluſion</hi> beeing drawne, is heerevnto added. That <hi>KINGS</hi> and <hi>KINGDOMS</hi> are heauenly <hi>Relatiues.</hi> And <hi>TRVTH</hi> hath ſaid it, That the Deſire of <hi>Money,</hi> is the roote of all <hi>Euill,</hi> &amp; that <hi>Couetouſnes</hi> is flat <hi>Idolatry.</hi> Which ſtanding moſt true,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.15. Coloſſ. 3.5.</note> it followes by Conſequence, that <hi>MERCHANDISING EX<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHANGE</hi> is that <hi>Laborinth</hi> of Errors &amp; prinate <hi>Practiſe,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by (though <hi>KINGS</hi> weare <hi>Crownes,</hi> &amp; ſeem abſolutely to raigne) particuler <hi>BANKERS,</hi> priuate <hi>SOCIETIES</hi> of <hi>Merchants,</hi> &amp; Couetuous Perſons, (whoſe End is <hi>Priuate gayne</hi>) are able to ſuſpend their <hi>Counſailes,</hi> &amp; controle their <hi>Pollicies:</hi> offering euen <hi>Bountie</hi> to <hi>KINGS,</hi> the Fountaines of <hi>Goodnes,</hi> &amp; lending <hi>Mony</hi> to <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne STATES</hi> and <hi>EMPERORS</hi> themſelues, that onely can make <hi>Coyne,</hi> and ſhould haue to giue largely, and lende vnto others. Thus making <hi>KINGS</hi> to be <hi>Subiects,</hi> and <hi>VAS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SALLES</hi> to be <hi>Kings.</hi> Such hath been the ſtrength of that Staine and Stay of <hi>Pietie,</hi> that contempt of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> that ſeede of <hi>Diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> that world of <hi>Warres,</hi> and Art of <hi>Witch-craft, VSVRIE.</hi> Such is and will be the power thereof at all occaſions: till <hi>KINGS</hi> and <hi>COVNSAILERS</hi> take their owne Charge in hand, and (next to <hi>RELIGION</hi> that ſanctifies all) relieue &amp; maintaine the <hi>Nurſe</hi> of <hi>IVSTICE,</hi> that rectifies all. To wit, <hi>free-borne TRAFFICK,</hi> I meane in <hi>ENGLAND,</hi> and <hi>Engliſh TRAFFICK.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In Magnis voluiſſe ſat eſt, ſunt caetera DIVVM.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="242" facs="tcp:15000:24"/>
               <pb n="243" facs="tcp:15000:24"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
